<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The conversion of a sinner faithfully translated out of Italian, by M.K.</title>
            <title>Breefe treatise exhorting sinners to repentance</title>
            <author>Luis, de Granada, 1504-1588.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1598</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 189 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 88 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72844</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16899.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124577</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900287</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900287</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150700</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72844)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150700)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1972:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The conversion of a sinner faithfully translated out of Italian, by M.K.</title>
                  <title>Breefe treatise exhorting sinners to repentance</title>
                  <author>Luis, de Granada, 1504-1588.</author>
                  <author>M. K., fl. 1580.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 85 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Thomas Creede, for I. P[arnell].,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1598]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Original title not traced.</note>
                  <note>An edition of Luis de Granada  "A breefe treatise exhorting sinners to repentance".</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Luis de Granada on A2r.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the All Souls College Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Repentance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Salvation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150700:1"/>
            <p>THE CONVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a Sinner: Faithfully tranſlated out of <hi>Italian, by M. K.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm. 36. verſ. 27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Declina a malo, &amp; fac Bonum.</p>
               <l>Leaue ſinne, ere ſinne leaue thee: do good,</l>
               <l>And both without delay:</l>
               <l>Leſſe fit, he will to morrow be,</l>
               <l>Who is not fit to day.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by Thomas Creede, for I. P.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150700:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150700:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Doo heere preſent vnto thy fauourable view (moſt curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and gentle Reader) this Pamphlet, which wanting a particular Patron, commeth (as it were) a begging vnto thee, for no leſſe then thy whole ſelfe, and that chiefly for thine owne good. The way to protect it, is to direct thy life by it, &amp; to ſuffer it to poſſeſſe thee, aſſoone as thou haſt poſſeſt it: which if thou be ſo happie to accompliſh, it will teach thee to win Loue by feare: Life by death: yea, euerlaſting happineſſe, by the tranſitorie troubles of this wretched world. And to giue it iuſt praiſe, in a word, it is a worke of the learned and ſpirituall <hi>Granado,</hi> aptly tranſlated by a vertuous Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, into our Engliſh.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150700:3"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Lamentationes</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let Dread of paine for ſinne in after time,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let Shame to ſee thy ſelfe enſnared ſoe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let Greefe conceiued for foule accurſed crime,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let Hate of ſinne the worker of thy woe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With Dread, with Shame, with Greefe, with Hate enforce,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To deawe the cheeks with teares of deep remorce.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Carmen.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>So Hate of ſinne ſhall make Gods Loue to grow,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So Greefe ſhall harbour Hope within thy hart:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So Dread ſhall cauſe the flood of Ioy to flow:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So Shame ſhall ſend ſweete Solace to thy ſmart.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So Loue, ſo Hope, ſo Ioy, ſo Solace ſweete,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shall make thy ſoule in heauenly bliſſe to fleete.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Vae.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Woe where no Hate doth no ſuch Loue allure,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Woe where ſuch Greefe makes no ſuch Hope proceed:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Woe where ſuch Dread doth no ſuch Ioy procure,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Woe where ſuch Shame doth no ſuch Solace breed.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wo where no Hate, no Greefe, no Dread, no Shame</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>No Loue, no Hope, no Ioy, no Solace frame.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>Non tardes conuerti ad Deum.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:150700:3"/>
            <head>A brief Treatiſe, exhorting ſinners to repentance, <hi>commonly called,</hi> The Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a ſinner.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sinners are commonly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to God, through feare and dread. Who if they read and well weigh holy writ, would tremble and quake, conſidering the iminent perils wherein they dwell, and would diuert from their wicked wayes, to the path of perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thereby the better to ridde themſelues from the gnawing gripes of a giltie conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and dreadfull torments due vnto ſin, which otherwiſe God threateneth vppon them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>The firſt Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E reade in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Scriptures, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God, before he defaced &amp; vtterly raſed the Citie of <hi>Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchodonozor</hi> king of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſayd
<pb facs="tcp:150700:4"/>to the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> in this wiſe:
<note place="margin">Iere 32.</note> Take a booke not written in before, and write therein, that which I haue ſaid vnto thée, againſt <hi>Iuda,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from the firſt day I began to talke with thée, euen vntill this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day, and publiſh it in the preſence of all the people, thereby to prooue, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Nation vnderſtanding the manifold miſeries I minde to bring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, will reuolt from their iniquities, that in ſo dooing, I may haue compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion vppon them, pardon their offences, and ceaſe to exerciſe the whippe of my wrath which I haue alreadie prepared. The Scripture addeth further, that <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch,</hi> Scribe to this Prophet, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing that which hee had written, in the open audience &amp; aſſembly of the people and Princes, ſuch horrour and feare fell amongſt them, that as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amazed, each beheld others, conſidering the heapes of woes and wretchedneſſe which then was vttered before them.</p>
               <p>This is the way (gentle Reader) that God then practiſed, and hath don many
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150700:4"/>times ſince, to daunt mens hearts, and violently to wreſt them from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, as the moſt effectuall and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible meanes that may bee founde to that purpoſe. For ſuch and ſo great are the things which the Scriptures and our fayth daylie telleth vs in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of vertue, and hatred of vice, that if men would reade them attentiuely, and ponder them aduiſedly, there is no doubt but their hearts would relent, and their fleſh tremble thereat, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the dreadfull daungers wherein they dwell. Wherefore the chéefeſt thing that the Prophet deſired aboue all others,
<note place="margin">Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2</note> for the redreſſe of this vncu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable maladie, was this, when hée ſaid: I would GOD this ſenſeleſſe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which are vtterlye deuoyde of counſell, did know, and throughly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſée what will happen vpon them, which if they did (as in dutie they are bound to doo) they could not poſſibly procéede or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue longer in their ſo crooked courſe of life. But they are all ſunke in the vile ſinke of ſenſuall delights: ſome hunt
<pb facs="tcp:150700:5"/>after honours, ſome for high promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and dignities, others beating theyr braynes day and night how to cloath curiouſly theyr carraine corps, and to accompliſh their carnall concupiſcence: haue no time, eyes, nor heart, to looke to their owne eſtate, and with the eyes of their minde, to meditate vppon theſe things, whereof the Prophet ſpeaketh, very properly,
<note place="margin">Oſea. 7</note> ſaying: Behold, <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> is like vnto a Doue deceiued, that hath no heart. For the wicked haue heart, wit, and will inough, to loue, to couet, and to count againe, and againe, vppon the pelfe of this world, but they haue neither witte nor will, once to thinke vppon the glory of the worlde to come, which is ſo infinite and ſo ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable, that if the leaſt part thereof bee exactly tried and examined in the minde, it would ſuffice to euacuate the filthy ſmoake which hath ſhut vp the eyes of their vnderſtanding, and to make them to acknowledge and confeſſe their owne errour. For this cauſe therefore beeing moued principally, I haue thought it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150700:5"/>requiſite to ſet downe certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions tending to this purpoſe, to the view of al that liſt to read or write them. Following héerein the example of the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> to ſhew not onely the gréeuous calamities that God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for the vniuſt, but alſo the perfect bliſſe that he hath prouided for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants the godly, that the euill diſpoſed returning from their wicked race, may be receiued into the fauour and mercy of God, releaſed of their treſpaſſes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all thoſe puniſhments which God menazeth vpon them in holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Chriſtian ought to conſider his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, that he is ſubiect to death, and muſt render a ſtraight account in the other life, of all his doings here. Where he ſhall diſcerne ſenſibly, the cryes and griefes intollerable, wherwith death &amp; ſinne rewardeth the vngodly, both here and in the world to come, there neither
<pb facs="tcp:150700:6"/>the beautie and fine feature of the body, neither the flattery of falſe fortune, nor yet the pompe of ſtately dignitie, ſhall ought preuaile to withſtand the wrath of the iuſt Iudge, againſt the wretched ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>Chap. II.</head>
               <p>TAking my firſt entry in that which is moſt obiected to our ſences: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that thou art a Chriſtian, and a man. Concerning thou art a man, hold it for a ground infallible, that thou ſhalt die: after which death, becauſe thou art a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, be ſure thou ſhalt giue vp a reckoning of thy life forepaſſed. Of this, the faith which we profeſſe wil not permit vs to doubt: that other, dayly experience doth confirme aſſuredly, ſo that none can ſhunne or eſcape the one nor the other. Be he Pope, Prince, or Emperour, there ſhall come a time wherein eyther hee ſhall ſée bright day continually, or vgly night inceſſantly. That time ſhall come without al doubt, yet thou knoweſt not when, whether
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150700:6"/>it will be to day or to morrow. In what time thou now readeſt this writing, whole and ſounde in all thy ſences and members, meaſuring the vayes of thy life according to thy buſineſſe, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, ſhalt ſée thy ſelfe in a bedde with a candle in thy hand, attending the dint of death, and ſentence pronounced againſt humaine kinde, which by no manner ſuite may bee releaſed. There ſhall be preſented vnto thée, the depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all earthly delights, the inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable payne and paſſion of death, the ende and laſt Pageant of thy life, the horrour of thy graue, the curſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of thy body, allotted to be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of woormes. But the wretched e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the ſoule will bee much more gréeuous vnto thée, which béeing yet in the body, knoweth not after an houre or two where his habitation ſhall be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned.</p>
               <p>Then in a moment, thou ſhalt ſée thy ſelfe ſette before the tribunall ſeate of God almightie, blaming and accuſing vnto him thine owne naughtie life.
<pb facs="tcp:150700:7"/>There thou ſhalt clearely diſcerne ſhe foule enormious crimes whereof thou art guiltie, and ſhall curſe ten thouſand times, the day in which thou diddeſt tranſgreſſe the commaundements of God, and the delight which ſtirred thée thereunto. Then ſhalt thou meruaile at thy ſelfe, how for ſo brickle pleaſures (as are thoſe which thou imbraſedſt) diddeſt hazard thy ſelfe to endure per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall torments, whereof thou now beginneſt to haue a taſte and ſmack, for that the ioyes béeing now quite vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away, and the doome due vnto thée approaching neare, that ſlender ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance which was in them looſing his eſſence and beeing, ſeemeth that it was nothing at all: But the remorſe and ſting wherwith they preſently prick and preſſe thy conſcience, appeareth to bée of ineſtimable force and efficacie.</p>
               <p>Perceiuing therefore, how for ſuch tranſitorie trifles, thou art at poynt to be bereaued of ſo incomparable felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, béeing abaſhed thereat, conſidereſt thine owne diſtreſſe, for that thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150700:7"/>runne out thy race, there reſteth no longer continuance of life, nor ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of repentance, neither thy world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fréendes, neither the Idols to whom thou haſt auowed the whole trauaile and terme of thy life, can aſſiſt or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour thée at all, yea thoſe things which earſt thou louedſt moſt tenderly, will be héere vnto thee the cauſe of gréteſt gréefe. Tell me I pray thée, when thou ſhalt ſée thy ſelfe plunged in this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie, whither wilt thou turne? what wilt thou doo? to whom wilt thou crye? To go backe it is impoſſible, ſo goe forwarde intollerable, to remaine as thou art, thou mayeſt not: what then wilt thou doo? Then ſayth God, by the mouth of the Prophet, the Sun ſhall not bee ſéene of the vngodly in the midday, and I will bring darkneſſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them in the bright day, and I will conuert their pleaſaunt ſports to bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter plaints: their dauncing and dally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to dolour and deadly dread. Oh what wordes bee theſe?
<note place="margin">Ezech. 32</note> The Sunne ſhall go downe in the midday, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:150700:8"/>ſhe huge heape of ſinne then ouerwhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the wicked, which ſéeing by the iuſt iudgement of God, the courſe of their life and time of repentance to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abridged, many of them are ſo appalled with feare, that they fall to flat diſpayre of the mildeneſſe and mercy of GOD. And abyding yet in the middeſt of the day, for ſo much as is remaynent of their mortall life, which is the very time to merit or not to merit: it ſéemeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that they haue no longer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to doo good or euill, but are vtterly excluded of both: verily the paſſion of feare is of great force and vehemencie, which maketh things that bee farre from vs, ſéeme to bee preſent: and of a trifle, rayſeth a tragedie. If the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of this, cauſeth them ſometime to quake, a little, what then ſhall the feare of their vndoubted and iuſt ieopardie cauſe them to doo? They béeing yet in this life, beginne to ſuffer ſenſibly the gréefe and reproach of the Reprobate, and in one very moment, are both quick and dead. For bewayling the preſent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150700:8"/>pleaſures which they muſt forſake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to ſéele the future miſerie which ſo much they feare. They holde them moſt happie which tarry here behinde, whereby they are prouoked to enuie, which greatly augmenteth their grieſe. To thoſe the Sunne goeth downe at noone dayes, for ſo much, as which way ſoeuer they caſte theyr eyes, they ſée themſelues debarred on euery ſide from acceſſe to Heauen, and that no beame or ſparke of comfort appeareth vnto them: for if they regarde the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God, they ſée how ſore they haue offended him: if they behold his iuſtice, they ſee him in a manner rigorouſly to ruſh vppon them: for that hitherto the time and tide hath béene at their becke, but now Gods turne is at hande: If they looke backe to their life forepaſſed, they ſée what accuſations groweth ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: If to the time preſent, they ſée them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to pecke ouer the pearch by péece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meale: If they looke forwarde a little further, they beholde the Iudge atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for their accounts. Alaſſe what
<pb facs="tcp:150700:9"/>ſhall the ſéely wretches doo, béeing at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teinted with ſo many treſpaſſes, and affrighted with ſuch furious feares at once? For this cauſe the Prophet ſaid, that the bright day ſhall be turned into darkeneſſe, thereby to giue vs notice, that thoſe things whereof the wicked are wont to take their greateſt conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, ſhould then be vnto them the cheefeſt cauſe of their diſcomfort. It is a good thing, I graunt, for a man to ſée his ſonnes, his friendes, his houſe, his worldly workes, and all that he loueth beſides: but then this chearefull light ſhall bee altogither conuerted to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found darkneſſe, for that all theſe things ſhall heape more heauineſſe, and ſhall become moſt bitter perſecuters of their affectioned louers. For as by nature and common cuſtome, we take no ſmall delight in the preſent poſſeſſion of thoſe thinges which we loue and like well: So likewiſe, the loſſe thereof bringeth exceſſiue gréefe. Therefore let the ſwéete children depart out of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſight when hée lyeth at poynt of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150700:9"/>death, and lette the mother alſo abſent her ſelfe, that ſhee may not giue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue by her preſence ſo many ſharpe aſſaults of ſorrowe. And his departure béeing into ſo far countries, his iourney through ſo ſtraunge and vnknowne waies, the pinching ſmart which hee abideth, will not permit him to haue confidence in any thing, neyther will graunt him to take his leaue of his fréends. If thou ſtandeſt now vppon the ſame termes I ſpake of, thou ſhalt well perceiue I haue not ſwarued from the truth: but if thou bee not yet come to this gulfe, beléeue them that haue made their paſſage before thee, as <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtes</hi> ſayth, They which paſſe ouer the Seas do tell ſtrange perils: if ſuch things doo occurre ordinarily before the departure, what ſhall happen after? If the eue and vigil be ſo dreadfull, how ſhall the feaſt it ſelfe bee, and day of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation? Tell me, I pray thée, what wilt thou thinks, when thou béeing depriued of this light and life, alone, poore and naked, without any other
<pb facs="tcp:150700:10"/>companion then thine owne guiltie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſhalt make thy appearance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>before the ſupernall ſeate of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Iudge, where a rigorous and ſeuers reckoning ſhall be erected of thée. There ſhall be no talk of hanging, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, or depriuing of this mortall life, but onely of the death and life eternal. If in the recordes of this rufull reckoning, thou be déepely charged with arrerages, debts, and treſpaſſes, what yrkeſome agonies ſhall thy poore heart then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure? How much ſhalt thou bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded? How ſore ſhalt thou repent thée to haue done amiſſe? How diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of comfort and counſell ſhalt thou bee The gréefe of the Princes of <hi>Iuda</hi> was excéeding great, when they beheld the pearſing ſworde and Souldiers of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacke</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to bee diſpearſed through the ſtréetes of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> when by theyr preſent plague and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, they recognized and confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed theyr former defects. But what is all this, béeing compared to the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and wee which there ſhall wrap
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150700:10"/>the wicked on euery ſide? what ſhall they doo? whither ſhall they flée? who ſhall bee theyr ſhield and befence? For there wéeping and wringing of handes doo not mooue compaſſion: there dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of former follies, is not accounted of: there no petition, no promiſe will be accepted: There no truce dayes or time of repentance can be graunted, for that hauing finiſhed the laſt pageant of the play, they cannot enter the ſtage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to play theyr part afreſhe: there neither eloquence, nor worldly wealth, nor fauour, may purchaſe pardon, for that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth:
<note place="margin">Prou. 11. Ezech. 17.</note> In the dayes of tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> richneſſe ſhal be of no force, and ſhall be deſpiſed vtterly: onely Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and equitie ſhall defend thée from death. But who can deſcribe or paint in his colours the ſeueritie of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</p>
               <p>This exhortation then béeing ſo good and ſo fruitfull, I beſéech thée deare brother, ſucke out the ſappe and ſwéete thereof for thy commoditie, ſcanning and conſidering attentiuely this, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon
<pb facs="tcp:150700:11"/>vpon thou muſt truſt and depend, as ſhe thing which concerneth thy perpetuall wealth or woe, and though herein are many things well worthy to bee noted, yet aboue al others, let theſe thrée things neuer be forgotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Then firſt, what grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous paine thou muſt then ſuffer, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing purchaſed by thy deſert Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation. The ſecond, how feruently thou wilt wiſh that thou haddeſt framed thy lifs according to his holy will and pleaſure. The third, that looke what pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thou wouldeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be glad to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, if it might be granted thée: now through mature deliberatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to aſſay and labour to liue in ſuch ſort as then thou wilt wiſh to haue liued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>At the day of iudgement, a Chriſtian muſt be accountable particularly of each little thought and fact committed in this life: where the ſinner being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted by the iuſt ſentence of God, ſhall be detruded to perpetuall paines, gaſtly ſhrikes, and to the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150700:11"/>profound darkneſſe of the infernall priſon: and there being ſcorched with the glowing coales which be neuer extincted through, wrath and fury, ſhall curſe both God and himſelfe, and calling eftſoones to minde, all the good and euill which he hath omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and committed, augmenteth thereby his owne annoy. He therefore that will not obiect himſelf to ſo many miſeries, muſt cal himſelfe to repentance in time.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>Chap. III.</head>
               <p>AFter death, followeth the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and ſpeciall iudgement of euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and after that the generall and vniuerſal iudgement of all men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhall be fulfilled y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle, <hi>Wee muſt all of force ſhew our ſelues before the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſeat of God, that euery one may giue an account of the good &amp; euil he hath done in this body.</hi> Many matters are to bee conſidered in this iudgement, but one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chéefeſt, is, to mark of what things we muſt giue a
<pb facs="tcp:150700:12"/>reckening. I will ſearch <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> diligently (ſaith God) with a candle in my hand. Such is the phraſe of the Scripture, whereby we ought to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed, how narrowly we ſhal be the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiſted and ſearched, in the very leaſt things that may be. For there ſhal not be one fond cogitation, nor one minute of an houre miſpent, but it ſhall bee ſkored vp in this reckoning. Who is not abaſhed and appaled at theſe words of our Sauiour, ſaying? Verily I ſay vnto you, that at the time of this audite, men ſhall be accountable of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry idle worde which they ſpeake vnad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſedly. Then if of theſe words which hurt or hinder no man, a reckoning ſhal be required, what ſhall be required, I pray you, of diſhoneſt and vnſéemely ſpéeches, of filthy imaginations, of hands bathed and imbrued with blood, of wanton lookes and vncontinent eyes? In figne, of the whole life imploied and conſumed in leawdneſſe and treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie? If this be true, as it is moſt true, what can bee inferred or gainſayed,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150700:12"/>why this iudgement ſhoulde not bee ſo rigorous as it is knowne to bee indéede? Howe full of ignominie ſhall hee bes, who in the open face of ſuch a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Senate, is proſſed and burthened with each vaine worde that hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him from the time of his natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? Who will not woonder at ſuch a ſtraunge demaunde neuer heard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? and who durſt to aduouche it, vnleſſe it had béene the wordes of Gods owne mouth? What King hath euer exacted an account of any his ſubiects to the value of of a pinne? O how ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent is the Chriſtian religion, howe pure is the ſinceritie which by it wee are taught, and with howe great care doth it demaunde the ſame puritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and how ſharply doth it puniſh our defects héerein. Further, how paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing great ſhalbe the ſhame and reproch of the reprobate, when all the miſchiefs which hitherto they haue cloſely coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the corners of their houſe, and all the brutiſh vehauiour of theyr youth, with all the ſecret ſores and feſtered
<pb facs="tcp:150700:13"/>carbunckles of their conſcience, ſhall be publiſhed in the theater, and open view of all the world. And further, who ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon ſuch ſure grounde, that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this, his colour doth not begin to chaimge copis? Some rather then they will diſcloſe the ſecrets of their heart to one man, in a place ſequeſtred from all acceſſe, béeing ouercome with ſhame, in eſchewing thereof, haue bidden the brunt of many huge perils: How ſhall they then be confounded whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their moſt couert drifts and treaſons ſhall bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in the preſence of God and his Angels, before ſo many millions of men and women, as haue béene from the beginning, are now and ſhall be hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? This confuſion ſhalbe ſo great, that as the Prophet ſaith, they ſhall cry vnto the hilles,
<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> ſaying: O ye hilles fall vpon vs, and cloſe vs in your Caues, that we may not ſhewe our ſelues with ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeding ſhame. But wo worth ye wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, your hope is fruſtrate, ye toyle againſt the tide, weighing the force of that ſentence definitiue, Go ye caitiues
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150700:13"/>into euerlaſting fire, long ſince prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for Satan and his adherents. What ſhall that curſed generation imagine then will become of themſelues hearing this? for if, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, we can ſcarce abide to heare his mildeſt wordes,
<note place="margin">Iob. 4.</note> who can abide thoſe thundring threats of his omnipotencie? Theſe words ſhall be ſo ſharpe and ſo pearſing, that at the verie inſtant, the earth ſhall open it ſelfe wide and large, and into the bottome and bowels thereof, ſhall be whirled topſie turuie, all thoſe, who,
<note place="margin">Iob. 2</note> as the ſame <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, here haue had their paradiſe and pleaſures, in ſundry ſortes of Muſicke and harmony, trifleling out their time and yeares in all kinde of mirth and iol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie. This fall and cracke of the earth, S. <hi>Iohn</hi> deſcribeth in his <hi>Apocalips,</hi> in this maner: I ſaw an Angell deſcending from heauen with great power, and with ſuch brightneſſe, that all the earth was lightned therewith, and hée cryed aloude, ſaying, The great Cittie of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon</hi> is fallen downe, and is made of the habitation of diuels, and the cage of all
<pb facs="tcp:150700:14"/>filthy and abhominable fowles. And further hée ſayd: I ſawe another migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Angell lifting vp on high a great ſtone, much like to a mylſtone, and did caſt it into the ſea, ſaying, With ſuch a violence ſhall the great <hi>Babylon</hi> bee throwne into the bottomleſſe pitte, and ſhall neuer recouer his eſtate againe. In this ſort ſhall the vngodly fall into the blacke and gaſtly priſon full of confuſion and vtter deſolation.
<note place="margin">Eſay 66.</note> But what tongue can expreſſe the innumerable &amp; ſundrie ſorts of torments, in that place addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the wicked? There their bodies ſhall be broyled with furious flames co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually: there their ſoules ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with the worme of conſcience, which will neuer ceaſe his gréenous gnawing. There ſhall be that inceſſant howling and gnaſhing of téeth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Scriptures treateth in ſo many places. There theſe vnhappie wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſurſeyſed with cruell diſpaire and rage, ſhall waxe wood againſt GOD and themſelues, in ſuche diſpiteous wiſe, that they ſhall deuoure their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150700:14"/>owne fleſhe, and in a franticke moode rent it with their nayles, craſhing their téeth togither, and ſpilling their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trailes with ſorrowe and ſighing, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming and denying continually their creator that hath adiudged them to ſuch ſharpe puniſhments. There euery of them ſhall crie out vpon his curſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and vnfortunate byrth, eſtſoones repeating thoſe pittifull bewaylinges, and wofull wordes of patient <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 3.</note> but with a minde and intent farre con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to his. Theſe bee the wordes. Curſt be the day wherin I was borne, and the night in whiche it was ſayd, A man is come into the worlde: let that day be turned into darkneſſe: let it not be reckoned of God, nor beautified with light: let it be ouerwhelmed with darkneſſe and ſhadowe of death: let it be full fraught with obſcuritie and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſſe: let that night be ouercaſt with a black cloude: let not that day be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among dayes and moneths of the yeare. Why did not death receiue me ſo ſoone as I was iſſued out of my mothers
<pb facs="tcp:150700:15"/>wombe? why was I not carried from the place of my byrth, ſtraight to my graue? why was I lulled in my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lap? or why did ſhe giue me ſuck? This ſhall be their melodie, their myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night mattens, their morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning prayer. O filthie tongues, which babble of nothing elſe but brawling and blaſphemie. O wretched cares, which heare no other things but wofull mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. O vnhappie eyes, whoſe obiect, is miſerie vppon miſerie. O wretched bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, who haue for your harbour a fierie fornace. In what caſe ſhall they then be, who héere earſt wallowed in wealth and wantonneſſe? O what fléeting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light hath wrought continuall gréefe? O what wofull habitations are addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for you? Now gone is all your gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant glée and iollitie, wherein you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted for a moment, for which ye now lament eternally. Now what doo your treaſures auayle you? where is your pompe and pleaſure become? the ſeuen fertile yeares are now ended quite, and in place thereof, are now ſuccéeded the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150700:15"/>ſeuen barren yeares, which ſhall ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the abundance of thoſe which are paſſed, that there ſhall not remaine any one ſhadow or ſhewe thereof. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all your former felicitie is drenched and wrapped vp in the waues of wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedneſſe, and are now driuen to ſuch ſtraights and ſcarcitie, that not ſo much as one droppe of water ſhall be granted vnto you, wherwith ye might ſomwhat aſſwage the raging thirſt which vexeth you ſo furiouſly: neyther ſhall your wonted proſperitie reléeue your miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but rather thereby ye ſhall be more fiercely afflicted. For therein is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed this ſaying of <hi>Iob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 21.24.25.</note> that the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred ſoppes of the vngodly, ſhalbe at the laſt deuoured with wormes. Which S. <hi>Gregory</hi> in his Moralls, expoundeth in this ſort: The memory of their wonted ioyes, maketh their preſent paine to ſéeme more bitter, by calling to minde how braue and frolike they haue bene, and how baſe and vile they now are come, and howe for loue of that which ſo ſoone ſlipte away, they ſuffer that
<pb facs="tcp:150700:16"/>which neuer ſhall haue end. Then ſhall they perceiue euidently the ſubtil ſlights of the enemie, and being called to their account, ſhall mutter too late theſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of <hi>Salomon:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sap. 5.</note> Woe vnto vs wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, howe apparaunt is it now vnto vs, that wée haue ſtrayed from the trade of trueth, that the light of inſtice hath not ſhined vpon vs, and that the ſunne of intelligence hath not riſen ouer vs.</p>
               <p>Wée haue waſted and wearied our ſelues in the crooked and crabbed way of wickedneſſe: but we haue not ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped one foote in the plaine and eaſie path which leadeth to righteouſneſſe. What are we now abettered by our Princely traine and treaſure? All theſe thinges are now vaniſhed as the fléeting ſhade, and as the ſwift Courſer chaſed vppon the ſpurre, as a ſhippe driuen with the tide and tempeſt, which leaueth behinde no print of his paſſage.</p>
               <p>This and ſuch like in the infernall pitte, ſhall bee the talke of thoſe which haue bene offendors. For that the hope and truſt of ſinne, is like vnto chaffe chaſed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150700:16"/>with the winde, or as the ſkumme and froath of the Sea diſpearſed with the waues, as the ſmoke ſodeinly diſſolued into the ayre, or as the remembraunce of a pylgrime paſſing by the way. Theſe be there the complaintes, and this the perpetual penance of the vngodly, which ſhall not aſſiſt them at all, becauſe the time is paſſed wherein they might haue bene reléeued hereby. Come therefore in the time of grace and repentaunce, and you that haue eares, receiue the ſounde aduiſe of our Lorde vttered by the Prophet, ſaying:
<note place="margin">Iere. 13.</note> Serue and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie God before the day be depriued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the darke night of death ſteale vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon you, and ere your féete be entrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, or ye ſtumble at that foule blacke hillocke. Therefore take the time and day whileſt ye haue it, for it ſhall be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into darkneſſe. And our Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, who better then any other, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the deapth of this daunger, aduerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth vs hereof in his Euangeliſt, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Luke 11.</note> Take héed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your hearts be not oppreſt with too much meate &amp; drinke, and with
<pb facs="tcp:150700:17"/>ouermuch care and turmoyle of this world, leaſt that dreadfull day catch you at vnwares, which will ſteale vpon you like a théefe, and vpon all thoſe which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habit vpon the face of the earth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore watch and pray continually, that you may be deliuered from theſe huge heapes of calamities, which hereafter will happen, that you being cleane and vndefiled, may be preſented before the ſonne of the pure Virgin, the promoter of all our auaile and profit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thoſe which haue loued God, and liued according to his will, ſhall be rewarded in Paradiſe, which is the glory and merit that good men do respect. Which notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any difference that is among the elect, bringeth a common comfort and pleaſure to them all, becauſe there is perfect chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and God is all &amp; in euery thing. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no other exerciſe is vſed there, or no other paine or trauaile, then to loue God, to laude and glorifie him inceſſantly for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150700:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <p>NOw that we haue declared the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation and ſharpe ſentence to be pronounced vpon the wretched ſinner: it followeth conſequently, that we treat likewiſe of the glorious recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence wherewith the righteous ſhall be endued, which is nought elſe, but that happie life and kingdome which God hath ordeined for his choſen people euen from the creation of all things, which is ſuch and ſo excellent, that neither with the tongue of men nor Angels it can be expreſſed. But that ye may haue ſome taſte of this, heare what S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> briefly ſaith in commendation hereof, in a certaine meditation of his, in this ſort: O life alotted by God to them that loue him, a liuing life, a life voide of care, a bleſſed life, a quiet life, a pleaſaunt life, a pure life, a chaſte life, a life enemie to death, a life that knoweth no gréefe, voyd of moleſtation, of ſmart, of anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, voyd of all corruption, voyd of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, not ſubiect to varietie, change
<pb facs="tcp:150700:18"/>or mutabilitie. A life full of beautie and perfection, where no enemie ſhall moleſt thée, nor no treſpaſſe offend thée: when is perfect vnitie, vnfeigned and holie loue: where all feare is far away: where is one eternall day, without alteration: where God is ſéene face to face, which is the foode of all that there abive. Swéet GOD, with an vnſatiable heart and greedie minde, I couet thy hidden trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and the more I long after them, the more I luſte and burne in deſire: conſidering thée my delight, my life and Sauiour, in contemplation whereof, I féele my ſelfe excéedingly refreſhed and reuiued. O moſte happie life, O very bleſſed kingdome, altogither with out death, and without ende, which doeſt not yéelde to any ſucceſſion or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of times, where is bright day continually, without interruption of night: there it is not knowne what mutation meaneth, where the tryum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Souldiour accompanied with a glittering crewe of Angelles, ſingeth vnto GOD without ceaſing, the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150700:18"/>praiſe of <hi>Sion,</hi> hauing gotten the crowne of euerlaſting felicitie. I would to God that my ſin, my gréeuous guilt, were forgiuen me: Thriſe bleſſed were my ſoule, if after this painefull pylgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, I might be worthy to ſée and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde thy glory, the beatitude, the beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the walles, and the gates of thy Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, thy ſtréetes, thy pallaces, thy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Citizens, thy worthie King, ſetled in his throne of magnificence. Thy walles are made of precious ſtones, thy gates are beautified with ſhining Pearles, thy ſtréetes are paued with pure gold, which reſounde and ring aloude with the peales of perpetuall praiſes. Thy houſes are buylded with quadrant ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, adorned with Saphyrs, thy bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and rafters are of golde, where no corruption can abide, nothing may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that is defiled. O <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> our mother, thou art braue and pleaſaunt in thy deuiſes, the force of no aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is felte in thée, neither any of thoſe diſcommodities are ſuſteyned whiche here we find. Thy ioyes are farre aboue
<pb facs="tcp:150700:19"/>any which this wretched life can yéelde vs. In thee is neuer founde night, darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, nor chaunge of times. Thy light iſſueth neither from lampe, nor from the Moone, nor yet from the ſtars, but God the light of all lightes, is ho which light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thée. The ſupernall Emperour kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth continuall reſidence in the middeſt of thée, enuironed and aſſiſted with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny millions of his miniſters. There the angelicall quires anſwere each to other melodiouſly: there the frutes of true nobilitie, doo yéelde a pleaſaunt ſent and ſpectacle to the beholders: there is cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated the feaſt of thoſe, who being ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly arriued from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottomleſſe ſea of theſe miſeries and miſhappes, are incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate in one ſocietie with thoſe which poſſeſſe eternall life: There is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the Prophets, the royall ranke of the Apoſtles, the inuincible hoaſt of innumerable Martyrs: there is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred conuent of graue Confeſſors: there are the true religious, the deuout wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, who deſpiſing all delights and dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance, haue conquered their fraile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150700:19"/>There are the virgins and younglings, which with their vertuous indnſtry, haue ſhunned ſhe allurements of this vile deceitfull world: There are the innocent lambs, who robbing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of all earthly pleaſures, doo now ſkip and leape for ioy, in theyr propper and peculiar houſes. And whatſoeuer difference there be in glory amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them, notwithſtanding the ſolace and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, is common to all: There chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ruleth béeing entire and perfect, for that god is all in all, whom they alwaies ſée, and ſéeing him continually, are euer enflamed with his loue, therefore they louing praiſe him, and prayſing loue him, all their exerciſe, all their endeuour, is to magnifie him without ceaſſing or intermiſſion. O how happie were I, and moſt happie, if after the diſſolution of this corporall priſon, I might heare the ſwéete muſicall ſongs of that cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall harmony, and ſing Pſalmes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation to the eternall king, of al the woorthy company of the moſt happie Cittie. Now happie ſhoulde I be, yea
<pb facs="tcp:150700:20"/>twiſe bleſſed, if I might attaine to this felicitie, to ſing &amp; ſtand before my King, my God, my guide, and to behold him in his glorie, as himſelfe hath promiſed to be ſéene,
<note place="margin">Ioh. 7.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſaid: O father, my deſire is, that all thoſe may be with me which thou haſt giuen me, that they may ſee the cleare brightneſſe which I had with thée before the foundation of the world. And all this is vouched out of S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</hi> Now tell me then what a cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full day ſhall that be, which ſhall ſo illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and clariſie thy courage, if at the full conſummation of this pilgrimage, thou paſſe from mortalitie to immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and in the ſame time that other<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> begin to droope, to doubt and dread, thou ſhalt beginne to lifte vp thy head, be cauſe the wiſhed day of thy redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion approacheth neare. Lifte vp th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> minde a little (ſaid S. <hi>Hierome</hi> vnto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> virgin <hi>Euſtochia</hi>) out of the dungeon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> this corrupt bodie, and ſetling thy ſelf before the gate of the heauenly taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, ſcan and conſider well the mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this thy preſent diſtreſſe, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious day that day ſhall be vnto thée
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150700:20"/>wherin the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> garded with a troope of pure virgins, ſhall be preſt to receiue &amp; welcome thee, and wherin thy Lord &amp; ſpouſe himſelfe, with all his holy Saints, ſhall méete thée, ſaying,
<note place="margin">Can. 2.</note> Come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and follow me quickly my loue, my delight, my doue, for now the wofull winter is paſſed, the ſharp ſhowres are ceaſed, the tempeſts &amp; whirlwindes are appeaſed, and here ſpring vp ſwéete fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant flowers in this lande of beheſt. This ſhall be then the delight &amp; conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that thy ſoule ſhall receiue before the high throne of that moſt bleſſed tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, before the angels, but ſpecially by him to whoſe cuſtodie thou were earſt committed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe &amp; all the reſt ſhall declare the ſundry tribulations, the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels &amp; perſecutions that thou haſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of Chriſt. <hi>S. Luke</hi> ſheweth,
<note place="margin">Act. 9.</note> that when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charitable <hi>Tabita</hi> deceaſed, all the widowes &amp; poore people beſought the apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in her behalf, ſhewing him their garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts which ſhe had made: the Apoſtle being moued thereat, praied vnto God inſtantly for ſo mercifull a
<pb facs="tcp:150700:21"/>woman, whereby ſhee was reſtored a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to life. What a ſingular com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſhalt thou then perceiue in thy ſoule, when thoſe bleſſed ſpirits ſhall take thée, and ſet thée before the diuine conſiſtorie of God, publiſhing thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts, and reciting orderly thy almes, thy prayers, thy faſting, the integrity of thy life, thy ſuſteining of wrong, thy pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in affliction, and temperance in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, with all thy other vertues and good déeds whatſoeuer? O what delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhalt thou then reape of euery good action here atchieued? howe ſhall the force and valure of vertue bee manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted vnto thée? There humble obedience ſhall triumph with victorie. There ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ſhal be rewarded, and the wel diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall be regarded according to theyr deſert. Beſides this, what inward and ſecret ſolace ſhal that be vnto thée, when thou ſéeing thy ſelfe arriued in ſo aſſured an harbour, ſhalt haue regard towards the courſe of thy dangerous nauigation paſſed, and ſhalt ſée the troubles and torments wherein thou liuedſt earſt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150700:21"/>ſhe wyles, the ambuſhes of the enemy, the cruell incurtions of théeues, which new thou haſt eſcaped. There it is where reſoundeth this ſong of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 93.</note> Were it not that the Lord was mindfull of mée, my ſoule ſhould haue hardly auoyded the infernall habitation. But ſpecially, when thou ſhalt perceiue how in this worlde offences are multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, how daily ſo many ſoules deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to hell and damnation: how among ſuch a multitude of caſtawayes, God would aſſociate thée into the fellowſhip of his choſen people, which ſhall be the inheritours of ſuch a renowmed king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. But that which paſſeth al this, is, to ſée the ſolemne feaſts and tryumphes which there are helde day by day, for the welcome of their newe brothers, who hauing ouercome the world, fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and performed the race of their pilgrimage, come to receiue the crowne of eternitie. O what ioy ſhall it be to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the accompliſhment of that which doo appertaine to the ſetting vp and new erection of the walles of the noble <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:150700:22"/>with what ſwéete embracing's and cullings ſhall they be welcomed by all the celeſtiall court, ſéeing them come laden and lugged with the ſpoiles of the vanquiſhed foe. There they ſhall enter with the victorious barons, with thoſe worthy women, which haue conquered the world, togither with theyr brickle nature. There likewiſe the vncorrupt virgins, murthered and martyred for their ſpouſe ſake Chriſt Ieſu, ſhall enter with double triumph: that is, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of the fleſh and of the worlds, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned and crowned with Garlandes, fraught with roſes and freſhe gréene flowers, all about their heads. In like maner, there litle boyes and gyrles ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering their tender yeares with diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vertue, ſhall come in to receiue the hyre and guerdon of their integritie. Where they ſhall finde theyr fréendes, knowe their miniſters, recogniſe theyr parents, and culling and kiſſing them affectionately, ſhall heare the glad ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings to bee made poſſeſſors of eternall felicitie. O how then ſhall the fruite of bertue taſte deliciouſly, although in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150700:22"/>times paſt the roote thereof ſéemed ſowre and vnſauery. Swéete is the ſhadowe after noone, the fountaine is pleaſaunt to the thirſty &amp; wearied waifaring man: ſléepe and reſt yéelde great comfort to him that hath trudged and toiled all day: but farre greater contentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peace brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the ſaints, after their weary war, ſecuritie after perils, and perpetuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe after infinit trauailes.</p>
               <p>The broyle of battaile is now appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to be armed it néedeth not, neither on the right fide; nor on the leſt. The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were armed, when they went to the land of promiſe, but after they had conquered the countrey, they laide aſide their weapons, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of them forgetting quite the feare and trouble of warre, they all were lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the harbor of reſt and quietneſſe, and enioyed the fruition of long deſired peace. There may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyes wearied with lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g watching, receiue their quiet ſléepes. Now may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubtil ſerpent attending to entrap vs, come out of his ambuſh: now may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> happy <hi>Hierom</hi> betake him to reſt,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:23"/>who made the night and day one, in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting his defaultes and treſpaſſes, encountering couragiouſly the cruell conflicts of our auncient enemie: there the horrible armours doo neuer ſound of that bloudie beaſt: there is no place forth: crooked craftie Serpent: there the venomous Baſiliſke dooth not effende the ſight nor his hiſſing is not heard, but the breath and ſweete ſounde that diſtils loth from the loue of the holy Ghoſt, here raungeth rounde about. Where is clearely diſcerned the royall magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of God himſelfe. This is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of reſt and ſecuritie, ſcaled aboue all the elements, where the dark cloudes and filthie vapours doo not ouerlappe the bright and pure aire. What happie things are ſaid of thée, O Citie of God? happie are they, ſaith <hi>Tobias,</hi> which loue thée,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 147.</note> and enioy thy peace. O my ſoule, extol and magnifie God, who hath deliuered <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> his holy city, from troubles and vexation. Nowe bleſſed ſhould I be, if hereafter in the remnant of my time, I might ſée the beautie and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150700:23"/>brightneſſe of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> whoſe gates ſhall be of Saphyrs, and of polliſhed Smaredges, the circuite of whoſe wall ſhall be of pearle and precious ſtone, the ſtréetes ſhall be of white marble, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laced with pure Alabaſter, and euery place reſoundeth with <hi>Alleluia,</hi> and voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of gratulation. O mery, ſwéete, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectable counſaile, O high renowmed glory, O bleſſed ſocietie, who ſhal be thoſe happie Chriſtians, picked or ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out to dwell in thée? It ſeemeth a hard thing to deſire thee, yet no man can liue without this deſire. O ſonnes of <hi>Adam,</hi> O wretched generation of men, how ſenſuall and abiect are your thoughts, for if this bee the viands or foode ye ought to feed vppon, what other thing doo you labour for? whereabout do you goe? what, will ye looſe a benefit ſo ineſtimable, rather then ye will trauaile a little? If this may bee obteyned with labour and paine, for mine owne part I deſire them, I call and cry to all the trauailes and toyles that may bee ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the world to come vpon me, that
<pb facs="tcp:150700:24"/>tribulations turmoile and toſſe mee at their pleaſure, that my body bee vexed with infirmities of all ſorts, and my minde afflicted with ſorrowe and anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: let both the one and the other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume me in griefe: let all the creatures of the worlde riſe vp and impugne mee: let me be the reproach of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the outcaſt of the world: let my life bee ſpent in dol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and diſtreſſe, and my yeares finiſhed in wofull wéepings: For all this I make no reckoning, ſo that after I may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate and haue my part with the Saints in Heauen, and may haue eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſt in the day of tribulation, and may aſcende to the people which are cloathed and adorned with that ſhining glory. Goe to now, O fooliſh world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, drudge and toile for high titles and dignities, erect lodgings and pallaces, enlarge the limits of thy poſſeſſion, let Kingdomes, and if thou wilt, lette the whole world be at thy commandement: yet for all this, thou ſhalt not be ſo great as the leaſt of Gods ſeruants, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth that which the worlde cannot
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150700:24"/>ginohim, and yet poſſeſſeth eternitie. Thou with thy riches and ryot ſhalt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the rich glutton in the dampe of eternall damnation: hee with poore <hi>Lazarus</hi> ſhall be caried vp with Angels, and conueyed into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the paines of hell, the ſinner can haue no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, for as the lot of the bleſſed is an vniuerſall proſperitie, which in it contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all good things: ſo the eſtate of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate is a general and vniuerſal miſery, which comprehendeth all euils in it ſelfe. For there the ſenſes of the conuicted ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſhal be tormented particularly, one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, proportionally to the crymes they haue committed, without all hope of end or releaſe of their grief, which ſhall be eternall, eager, infinit, ſharpe, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termiſſion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>Chap. V.</head>
               <p>THe leaſt part of theſe rewardes, were inough to ſtir vp our earthly and lumpiſh hearts to doo much
<pb facs="tcp:150700:25"/>more then that which wee are eni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o by the commaundements of God. But what if with this glory exceeding all meaſure, we adioyne in like manner the vnmeaſurable puniſhments proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for the wicked? For that thoſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not there be reuealed with this ſaying: What if I be a caſtaway? no other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couenience enſueth thereof, then ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to ſee the glory of God, and to be hereafter as though I neuer were, not knowing good nor euill. But they miſſe in their reckoning, béeing allotted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force to take one of theſe vnequall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, that is, eyther to be glorified with Angels, or accurſed with Diuels: to rule with God eternally, or to burne in hell perpetually. The one of theſe twaine they muſt néedes elect for the place of theyr perpetuall abode. Theſe bee the two baſkets which God fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed in a figure to the Prophet before the Gate of the temple, the one of them filled with dilicate and holeſome figges: the other full of ſuch filthy and vnſauery figges, that euery man abhorred to taſte
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150700:25"/>or touch them. Which ſignifieth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe then the oddes and difference of two fortes of people: the one is of the choſen, to whom God hath beſtewed his mercies bountifully: the other of the abiects, to whom God extendeth the heauie hand of his iuſtice. And the lot of the firſt ſort is ſo excellent floriſhing, and that of the others ſo wofull &amp; wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, that the greatneſſe of theſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames, ſo much differing betwéene themſelues, cannot be ſpecified by any words. But omitting all other conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, the ſtate of the happie is an vniuerſall felicitie, wherein all good things are conteined: and contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the condition of the wicked, is the hauen where arriueth all vnhappineſſe, the nourſe of ſorrow, and harbour of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe. All the miſeries which are in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to this life, be miſeries in ſpeciall, and therefore doo not torment all our members generally, but one or ſome of them alone. For example hereof, we ſee ſome men greeued in their eyes, ſome in their eares, many in their ſtomacks,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:26"/>others in their bellies, and not a fewe at the very heart. Yet none of theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities doo vexe all the ſences vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally at one inſtant, but ſome of them particularly. Notwithſtanding, the ſmart is oft full ſharpe and vehement, and the night ouer tedious to him that abideth either of theſe gréefes, be it but the aking of a toothe or gumme. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit now, that a certaine man ſhoulde ſuffer ſuch an vniuerſall puniſhment, that no member, ſence, or ioynt, ſhould bee frée from peculiar tormentes, and that at one very inſtant hée muſt abide moſt bitter paines in the head, in his eyes, in his téeth, eares, ſtomacke, liuer, heart, and to be ſhort, in all the other members and ioyntes of his bodie, and that hée laie in this perplexitie vppon a bedde, féeling the ſeuerall gréefes aſſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to euery member. What exceſſive forrow ſhould he ſuffer, thinkeſt thou, which were tormented in this ſorte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or what thing coulde be more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pittifull to beholde? If thou ſaweſt a dogge in that diſtreſſe, it would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150700:26"/>perforce moue thee to compaſſion. This deare brother (if any compariſon may be vſed herein) is that, which not for the ſpace of one night, but for euer, is ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the pitte that perpetually burneth with fire and brimſtone. For as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly do gréeuouſly offend God with all their ſences &amp; members, making them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtruments to further their franticke follies &amp; exceſſes: ſo by the ordinance of God, there they are all torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, &amp; euery of them abideth his proper puniſhment. For there the incontinent eyes ſhall be afflicted &amp; affrighted with the vgly ſight of diuels: the eares with confuſed cryes and complaints: the noſe with the intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable ſtenche of that filthy denne: the taſte, with raging thirſt and famine: the féeling, and all the body beſides, with pearcing colde &amp; heate: the imagination ſhall be tormented with the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of preſent paine: the memorie, by hauing ſtill in mind y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſures paſſed: the vnderſtanding, with co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration of the glorious kingdom loſt, &amp; curſed co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is hapned. The diuine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb facs="tcp:150700:27"/>tures ſignifieth vnto vs this pluralitie of paines, where it ſaith, that in hell ſhall be famine,
<note place="margin">Mar. 15. Pſal. 10.</note> thirſt, wéeping, and gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of téeth, the two edged ſword, the ſpirites and creatures of reuenge, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, wormes, ſcorpions, bytles, ſowre ſaſages, water diſtilled of gall, ſtormy tempeſtes, and other ſuch like annoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances. By which it frameth and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to our preſence, an euident patterne of the diuers and dreadful plagues prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed in hell.
<note place="margin">Exod. 10.</note> Finally, there ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and outward darkneſſe, both of the body and minde, farre more obſcure then thoſe of <hi>Egypt,</hi> which might be felt and touched with the hand. There ſhall be fire, but not ſuche as we vſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, which ſmarteth a little, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth quickly: but ſuch as is moſt fit for that place, that is, which afflicteth vehemently, and neuer ceaſeth to tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. If this be true, how can it be, that thoſe whiche beléeue and confeſſe the ſame, ſhould line ſo looſely, and ſléepe in ſuch ſecuritie? What daunger, what tedious toyle would not any man glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150700:27"/>vndertake, rather then he would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure one day, yea one houre, the leaſt of theſe torments? Why then to ſhun a perpetuitie of calamities ſo tragicall, doo they not imploy themſelues to ſo eaſie trauaile as that which is requiſite to the following of vertue? This thing were inough to ſequeſter a mans ſoule from his ſences, and to bring him to an extacie, that deliberateth aduiſedly here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon. Yet if among theſe huge heapes of miſeries, were any hope of ende or redreſſe, it woulde quallifie ſomewhat their gripings corſies: but alas, they find it there farre otherwiſe, for the gates of comfort are cloſed vp on all ſides. In all kinde of heauineſſe that may happen in this life, reſteth alwayes ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, wherein the afflicted may repoſe himſelfe, as that which is adminiſtred either by reaſon of time, fréendes, or company of many whiche doo partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate with him in the ſame miſhap, or by hope to be releaſed at laſt, may mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate their maladie: But in this euill onely, the cundits of grace are ſo ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:28"/>and the paſſages of common com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort ſo interrupted, that theſe vnhappie creatures can finde fauour on no ſide, neither from heauen, neither from the earth, neither of the time paſſed, nor preſent, nor of that to come, nor of ought that can be elſe, but they ſéeme to be preſſed and pearſed of all partes, and that all creatures co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpire againſt them, whereby at laſt they ware wood and wrath with themſelues. This is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme ſtraightneſſe, whereof the wicked bewayle themſelues by the Prophet, in this ſorte:
<note place="margin">Pſal. 17.</note> The dread of death hath hedged me in on euery ſide, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernall frightes haue inuironed met round about, in ſuch wiſe, that whereon ſoeuer they péepe or prie, their obiect is alwayes miſerie exempted of mercie. The Virgines whiche ſtoode preſt at the Pallace of their ſpouſe, were recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in,
<note place="margin">Matth. 15.</note> as the Euangeliſt ſaith, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deinly the gates were locked. O perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall pinning faſte, O immortall inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, O gate of comfort which neuer ſhall be opened, which is as though he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150700:28"/>had ſaide, Cloſed is the porte of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, ſhut is the doore and hatch of hope and interceſſion, of grace, of conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of meriting any more. The ſixe daies are vaniſhed, wherin Manna was to be gathered, but the Sabboth it could not be founde, wherfore he muſt faſt alwaies, which would not prouide for himſelfe in time. The y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le ſluggard (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) fearing the colde will not till his grounde in the Winter, whereby he ſhall begge in the ſommer, and nothing ſhall be giuen him. And againe, He that laboureth in the ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and time of harueſt, is diſcréete: but he that then betakes him to ſleepe, is the ſonne of perdition. What greater confuſion can there be then that which hapned to the riche myſer, who might haue purchaſed his place in heauen with the crums of bread that fell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his table: by his couetouſneſſe in deteyning that litle, is now brought to ſuch penury himſelf, that he craueth, &amp; ſhall craue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually one drop of water, &amp; ſhal neuer obtaine it. In whoſe heart doth not this
<pb facs="tcp:150700:29"/>requeſt of that wretch moue a remorſe. O father <hi>Abraham,</hi> pittie my caſe, and ſend <hi>Lazarus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 16.</note> that he may dip the top of his finger in the water, and may touch my toong therewith, for this fire tormenteth me out of meaſure. What leſſe petition could be demaunded then this? for he durſt not requeſt one veſſell of water, neither would he that <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> ſhould wet all his hande, nor his whole finger, (which is to be wondred at) but only the toppe of his finger, and yet it would not be graunted vnto him. By which thou ſeeſt how cloſe the gates of grace are ſhulte, and howe farre the prohibition and curſe ſtretcheth, which is prepared for the vngodly, ſith they cannot get ſo ſmall a matter. In ſuch ſort, that caſt they their gaſtly lookes which way they will, let them extend their hand to what place them liſt, they ſhall finde no crum of comfort, be it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo ſmall. And as one fallen into the ſea, plunging in the deapth of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, can finde no perfect footing, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſtretching out his arme, catcheth
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150700:29"/>and graſpeth round about in vaine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now euen ſwallowed in the gulfe: So ſhall it happen to the accurſed crue, to whome the worlde is without any ſtabilitie, for wading in the waues of ſuch woe &amp; wretchedneſſe, and alwaies ſtriuing with death, without truſt or ſtay of any ſuccour to leane vnto. Of all the gréefes which is ſuffered in that miſchéeuous place and harbour of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, this is the greateſt: for if theſe puniſhmentes were determinable by any time, yea though it were a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande yeares, or a hundred thouſande million of yeares, it were ſome kinde of comfort, for that which hath end, is not altogither to be diſpraïſed: but the paine of the wicked ſhall be eternall, and the time of their diſtreſſe ſhall be coequall with the diuine glorie of God: ſo long as God ſhall liue, ſo long ſhall they dye: and when God ſhall ceaſe to be that he is, then ſhall they likewiſe leaue to be that they are. O dying life, O liuing and immortall death, I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I ſhould call thée life or death, for
<pb facs="tcp:150700:30"/>if thou be life, why dyeſt thou? if thou be death, how doeſt thou ſtill endure? I will not therefore call thée the one nor the other, for that neither the one nor the other, conteyneth ought that good is. Life hath his limits, and death dureth but for a time, which much auayleth to the aſſwaging of ſorrowes, but in thée are neyther boundes nor ſpace at all. What then art thou? Verely thou art the penaunce of life, and the plague of death, for thou haſt the ſting and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of death euerlaſtingly, and of life thou haſt the perpetuitie without inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. GOD ſpoyled both life and death of their happineſſe, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to thée, that which was left for the perpetuall puniſhment of the vngodly. O curſed confection, O bitter pill, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt vtterly of all the benefites and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights that floweth from our ſwéete Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour Chriſt, which is the foode that all wretched ſinners féede vpon. I wiſh therfore, deare brother, that not ſildome thou wouldeſt erect thy earthly minde to the conſideration of this eternitie, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150700:30"/>as a beaſt of the world wouldeſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times make thy repaſt thervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which that thou mayeſt performe effectually, propone before thy eyes of vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, the affliction that a ſicke man ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth in one night, ſpecially if hée be ſeaſed with ſome ſharp infirmitie. Mark I pray thée, how oft he turneth &amp; wallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth in his very bed, how he can take no kinde of reſt, how the night ſeemeth ſo long vnto him, that he reckoneth euery houre of the clocke, &amp; each houre ſéemeth a day long. He looketh &amp; longeth for the light, which nought or little auaileth to moderat his miſery. Then if this ſorrow bee ſo great and inſupportable, what ſhall the paine be of that eternall night, which hath no morning nor dawne of day? O profounde darkeneſſe, O night perpetuall, O night accurſed by Gods owne mouth, the light whiche was wont to lift vp it ſelfe in the morning, is not ſéene in thée. Conſider nowe what a torment it is to liue alwayes in ſuche a night as this is, not couched in a ſofte bedde, as a ſicke man is,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:31"/>but rather in a fornace flaming with fires. What ſhoulders can be able to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide theſe ſo feruent heates? what heart will not melt with ſorrow, to continue in ſuch torment for euer? Which of you (ſaith God by the Prophet) can ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine that conſuming fire, and liue in that exceſſiue heate? O dreadful threats, if that a man cannot endure poſſibly to put the toppe of his finger vppon one glowing coale, whileſt a <hi>Pater noſter</hi> is ſaide: howe ſhall he abide to broyle both bodie and ſoule in theſe eternall flames, which are ſo fierce and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that comparing them to thoſe which here we ſée in this world, ſéeme of no more force then fire paynted on the walles? Is there any iudgement in the earth? haue men vnderſtanding? doo they perceiue the weight of theſe wordes and threates? thinke they that thoſe are deuices faigned by Poets? or doo they perſwade themſelues that it toucheth ſome others, and perteineth not to them? Wherein they are much deceiued, and ſottiſhly féede their foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150700:31"/>fancie, ſith it is verified by the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall trueth, ſaying, Heauen and earth ſhall decaie, but my word ſhall neuer want his force and vigour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We haue great cauſe to be the ſeruants and affectionate friends of God, as well for the gifts of nature bestowed vpon vs, and the infuſion of grace which we haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and hereafter hope to receiue, as alſo for dread of his wrath. Among which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and graces granted vnto vs, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments are moſt precious. Hauing then receiued ſuch and ſo many benefits of him, we ought not to ſhewe our ſelues ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that all his troubles and trauels ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red here on earth, may be for our behoofe and profit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>SOme man peraduenture will mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel why I ſhould accumulate ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons to iuſtifie this that I haue begunne, and to confirme an approued veritie, and a thing ſo commendable as
<pb facs="tcp:150700:32"/>is that atchiuing of vertue, but this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is not addreſſed to that ende, nor to extenuate any doubt that may be in a matter ſo manifeſt.</p>
               <p>But for that monſtrous is the malice of our corrupt minde, and the conflicts very cruell which ſtriue to deſtroy the ſoueraintie of renowmed vertue, it is requiſite that her bulwarkes be of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ſtrength to beare the brunt and ſhocke of all aſſaultes. But for my bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proofe and progreſſe of this matter, it ſhall not be amiſſe to adioyne here vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, howe much we are bounde to the ſeruice of God, not onely for hope of the hire which we expect at his handes, nor for dread of his iuſtice, but chéefely for thoſe good things which by him we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently enioy. For if all creatures im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their benefactours, and bruite beaſtes acknowledge them by whome they haue bene reléeued: yea, if the lawe of thankeſgiuing be of ſuch force, that the fierce Tygres, Lions, and Serpentes, yéelde to her ſegnioritie, and liue vnder her lore, howe ſhall I eſcape to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150700:32"/>more cruell then thoſe beaſtes, if I ſhould not loue and magnifie him, who hath bene ſo beneficiall vnto me? What is there either in me or without me, whith is not iſſued from the bountie of God? Thou Lorde haſt created my ſoule to thine owne image and ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, thou haſt diſpoſed the organes of my bodie, and beautified it with ſuch feature and varietie of members and ſences, that regarding well the curious cunning of the worke, appeareth that it can be wrought by no other artificier then thy ſelfe. Thou haſte and doeſt ordaine daily all thinges neceſſarie for the preſeruation of this thy woorke, thy prouidence is my guide, thy hand doth ſuſtaine me, thy creatures ſerue me, thy medicines heale me, thy foode doth nouriſh me, thy Angels guard and kéepe mée, thy wiſedome inſtructeth mée, thy mercy prouideth for mée, and thy patience ſupporteth mee: Finally, all that I haue, are thy goods, thy grace, and thy mercy.</p>
               <p>For who giueth mee my eſſence,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:33"/>to be that I am, but thou that art the Fountaine of all eſſence and béeing.</p>
               <p>By whoſe benefite doo I liue, if not by thine, which giueſt light and life to all them that breath? who giueth me iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and vnderſtanding, if not thou which art the lampe of eternall light? Therefore what ſhould a man doo for ſuch a one, who hath him ſo much his benefactour? Why ſhould he not ſerue him with all his forces both of bodie and minde, who hath made him all, and doth preſerue him all, both bodie and ſoule, and by whoſe direction he is gouerned altogither? Wherfore if we be ſo much bounde vnto him for his benefites gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vs by nature, how can we gratifie him ſufficiently for thoſe his giftes of grace? How canſt thou counteruayle his curteſie, who amongeſt ſo ſundry ſorts of people and nations of Infidels, hath ſingled thée out for himſelfe, hath created thée a Chriſtian, and hath wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed thée with the water that diſtilled from his precious ſide, and there hath adorned thée for his ſonne, and hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſted
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150700:33"/>thée with all habites and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes that are requiſite for that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie? But after, when againe thou were fallen from this preheminence, who can declare how patiently hée did holde thée vp, when thou ſinnedſt? with what eyes did he beholde thee, when thou madeſt no reckoning of him? how carefully did hée guard thée, when thou diddeſt procraſtinate thy returne vnto him? with how many holy inſtincts did he ſtirre thée? with how many harolds did he ſommon thée to come, that at the laſt, forſaking thy former follies, ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt bowe to his holy will and bent?</p>
               <p>But what ſhall I ſay of that ſupernall grace, of that moſt excellent benifite of our redemption? O Lorde the heauens bleſſe and extoll thée, and the Angelles ſing prayſes of thy merueilous workes. What néede haddeſt thou of our auaile, or how could our annoy bee preiudiciall vnto thée? If I offende (ſayth <hi>Iob</hi>) what hurt is it vnto him? and if thine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties abounde, what harme taketh hee thereby? and if thou doo well, what is he
<pb facs="tcp:150700:34"/>ſhe better therefore? But what commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie? what reward can he reape at thy hands, who is God omnipotent, ſo rich and ſo frée, and far from all wracke and woe? that GOD (I ſay) whoſe wealth, whoſe power, whoſe wiſedome can be neither augmented nor diminiſhed: who neither before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution of the world, nor after he had made all things, is one iot more or leſſe then hee was before: nor if all the angels and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde ſhould be ſaued, and ſhould praiſe him perpetually, is any whit the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier: nor if they all were damned and did blaſpheme him, is leſſe glorious at all. This ſo great a lord, not drawne nor driuen by any ſtraights at all, but of méere grace and bountie, whilſt our acts of hoſtilitie were yet in freſh memorie, was content to encline the heauens of his royall maieſtie, and to deſcend into this Caue of calamities, to cloath him with the veſture of our mortalitie, to charge himſelfe with the déepe debt of al our ſins, and for ſatiſfaction thereof, to endure ſuch torments as were neuer
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150700:34"/>ſuffered in this world. For my ſake, O Lorde, thou waſt borne in a ſtall: for mée thou waſt laid in a manger: for mée thou waſt circumciſed the eight day: for me thou waſt conueyed into <hi>Egypt:</hi> for me (to conclude) thou waſt perſecuted and turmoyled with a number of infamies: for me thou watchedſt: for me thou tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailedſt: for me thou ſwetteſt: for mée thou didſt wéepe: for me thou haſt proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued all thoſe euils which my enormous crimes haue deſerued, thou béeing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and guiltleſſe. Finally, for mée thou waſt apprehended as a malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, abandoned of thy fréends, ſolde, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, preſented before the tribunall ſeate of thoſe iudges, where thou were accuſed, bufferted, defamed, whipped, ſpitted at, ſcratched, condemned, cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, blaſphemed, pierced with a ſpeare, dead and buried. Therefore with what deſert of mine, can I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite my ſelfe, I will not ſay of all theſe courteſies, but of the leaſt drop of blood ſhed out of thy holy ſide, for me vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy wretch. How is it poſſible that
<pb facs="tcp:150700:35"/>I ſhould loue him ſufficiently, who ſo hath loued me, ſo hath created me, ſo hath redéemed me, and hath bought mée ſo dearely? If I be lifted vp from the earth (ſayth our Sauiour) all things ſhall be drawne after me. But with what chaines, with what violence?</p>
               <p>With the force of loue, and with the bondes of his benefits. With the rope of <hi>Adam</hi> (ſayth our Lorde) I will draw the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me, and with the knot of loue. Therefore who will not bee lifted vppe with this draught? who will not ſuffer himſelfe to bee catcht and caried with ſuch chaines? If one little drop of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter falling continually vppon a ſtone, will pearce and breake it at the laſt, how ſhall not the bonds of ſo many benefits be inough to rent my ſtony heart a ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? And if the very earth wrought in the feruent heat, is ſometimes conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into fire, how ſhall my heart be frée from burning, béeing ſo beſet with the glowing coles of ſuch vnmeaſurable loue? if it bee ſo haynous an offence not to loue this Lorde, what ſhall it be to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150700:35"/>him, to deſpiſe him, and to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe his commaundementes? How canſt thou haue any heart or hand to offende thoſe handes which haue bene ſo bountifull vnto thée, which for thée were ſpread vpon the croſſe? When that laſciuious woman beſought the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> that he would betray his maiſter, the holy man repelled her with this ſaying, Behold, O wretched wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, what truſt my Lord hath repoſed in me, to put all that he hath into my handes, except thée his wife, therefore with what face can I commit this vila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie againſt my Soueraigne? Which is as if hée had ſayd, If my Lord hath béen ſo friendly affectioned towards me, if he hath committed all that he hath to my cuſtodie, if in ſuch wiſe he hath fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied and honoured me, that in me only it reſteth to diſpoſe of his affaires: how may I, béeing tyed with the bonds of ſo many benefites, haue any handes at all to offende a Lorde ſo liberall? And it doeth not content him to ſay, It is no reaſon to offende him: but, How can I
<pb facs="tcp:150700:36"/>offend him? for the greatneſſe of good turnes, doo not onely reſtraine the will, but in a manner all power and poſſibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to annoy the benefactor. And it bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth faſt both the handes and the féete of a man, that he cannot ſtriue againſt it. Wherefore if theſe kind of ceremonies, as to bee gratefull for good turnes bée of ſo great force, what ſhall we thinke of the benefites of God? That man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to <hi>Ioſephs</hi> fidelitie all his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and God hath put into thy hands all that he hath. Conſider then howe much Gods treaſures are more woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy then any that <hi>Pharao</hi> did poſſeſſe, for that ſo much more is this which thou enioyeſt, then was that which <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> did receiue. But tell me what thing hath God, which he hath not giuen into thy hands? heauen, earth, the ſunne, the moone, the ſtarres, the ſea, birdes, fiſhes, trées, beaſts, and finally all that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined vnder the golden globe, he hath beſtowed vppon thée: and yet not that onely which is héere belowe in earth, but likewiſe all that is in the Heauens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150700:36"/>which is the glory, the riches, and the delights of Angels and Saintes, which are there praying buſily for thy commoditie. All things (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) are yours, whether it be <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Paul.</note> or <hi>Apollo,</hi> or <hi>Peter,</hi> bee it the worlde, bee it life, bee it death, bee it the time preſent, or that to come, all is yours, for that all ſerueth for your behoofe: and yet not that alone which is aboue the heauens, but the Lord of heauen himſelfe, hath giuen vs his onely ſonne, after ſundry ſorts, ſometimes as a patron, ſometimes as a defendor, ſometimes as a ſauiour, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for a teacher, ſometime for a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, ſometime for a rewarde, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time for a conſeruation, ſometime for a remedie, and for each other our néed. The Father hath giuen vs his ſonne, the ſonne hath merited for vs the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, the holy Ghoſt hath made vs meritorious of GOD the Father himſelfe, from whome floweth the ſtreames of all felicitie. Therefore if this father (as the Apoſtle ſayth) hath giuen vs his onely ſonne, which was
<pb facs="tcp:150700:37"/>the greateſt gift he could beſtow on vs, howe will hee not deliuer vnto vs with him all other things whatſoeuer? Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if it bee true that God hath giuen vnto thée al that he hath, if he hath wrapt thée faſt with obligation of ſo many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefites: howe is it poſſible that thou ſhouldeſt moleſt or gréeue ſo liberall and bountifull a benefactour? If it be a grée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous crime, not to be thankfull for ſo good turnes: what ſhall it be to adioyne to ingratitude, the contempt and offence of the benefactor? If that young man founde himſelfe in ſuch bondage, and ſo impotent to annoy him who had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his fidelitie the charge of his houſe: what heart or courage canſt thou haue to offend him, which for thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe hath created both heauen &amp; earth? O more vngrateful then the very beaſt, O more cruell then the Tigres, O more inſenſible then the ſenſleſſe creatures, not to conſider ſo great a fall: for what beaſt, what Lion, what Tiger, did euer hurt the man that did them good?</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writeth, that a dogge
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150700:37"/>all one night howled and bewayled his maiſter, which was ſlaine by his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: whither repairing many the next morning, to view the dead corpes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom the murtherer alſo made his appearance, whome ſo ſoone as the dog beheld, furiouſly ranne vpon him, in ſuch wiſe, that the malefactour was detected thereby. Wherefore if a dogge for a péece of bread did ſhewe ſuch loyall loue to his maiſter: howe canſt thou become ſo vngratefull, to ſuffer thy ſelfe in the lawe of reaſon and humanitie, to be inferiour to a dogge? If that beaſt was wroth againſt him that had ſlaine his maiſter: what wilte not thou bee wroth againſt them that haue killed thy Lorde and Soueraigne? and who are thoſe that haue killed him, but only thy offences? theſe are euen they that tooke him, that bounde him, that whip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him, that nayled him to the Croſſe. For all the torments had not bene ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for this exployt, had they not bene aſſiſted by thine offences. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then doeſt thou not waxe wood a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:150700:38"/>theſe ſo cruell murderers which haue bereaued thy Lord of his life. Wherefore, ſéeing him dead in thy ſight, doth not thy affection increaſe towards him, and thy wrath towards ſin, which hath killed him, knowing that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer in this world hee hath ſaid, done, or ſuffered, was to imprint ſuch an hatred in our hearts againſt ſin, that we ſhould deteſt it vtterly. To ſlay ſinne he dyed himſelfe, and to binde it hand and foote, hath ſuffered himſelfe to be bound vpon the croſſe. Why then wilt thou make fruſtrate all the labours and paines of Chriſt? Wilt thou run headlong into the thraldome and bondage fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence Chriſt hath deliuered thée with the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of his precious blood? why doeſt thou not tremble and ſhiuer at the onely name and ſounde of ſin, now that thou haſt ſéene the extremities that Chriſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the remoouing thereof? what could GOD doo more to reſtraine vs from ſinne, then to ſet himſelf before vs bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed pitifully vpon a croſſe? who durſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe God, if hee ſaw heauen and earth
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150700:38"/>open before him? yet much more it is to ſée God ſtretcht vppon a croſſe, then all this. Wherfore, whoſoeuer is not ſtirred with this motiue, there is nothing in the wide world, whereby he may be reduced from the fonde and perillous iourney wherein he is entred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God doth not ſuffer thoſe to want any thing neceſſarie to this world, which bee righteous, and do keepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, but doth comfort them with his graces and gifts infinitly, as well temporall as ſpiritual, preſent, as thoſe to come. Whereof the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly haue exceeding great ſcarcitie, for that noble vertue is euermore aſſociated with all good things, and contrariwiſe, vice with miſchiefes and miſeries.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>BUt peraduenture thou wilt ſay, that all theſe things before treated of, are right iuſt, as well y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good things as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> evil
<pb facs="tcp:150700:39"/>yet deſireſt to ſée ſome preſent motine, which ſhould ſerue to eleuate thy heart, fithe the thinges obiected to our daily viewe, doo moue vs more forcibly. Of theſe things alſo we will giue thée thy glut, and thou ſhalt haue thy ſacietie of that thou deſireſt. For admit our Lord had kept the beſt wine and meate fill the ende of the banket, yet for all this, he will not that his ſeruants ſhould faints with famine by the way: for he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth very well if they ſhould be ſo ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, they cannot continue in their iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Wherefore he ſaid vnto <hi>Abraham,</hi> Feare not, O <hi>Abraham,</hi> for I am thy defendour, and thy rewarde ſhall be great. By theſe words two things are promiſed, one in this preſent life (as he was his defendour in all things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning therevnto) the other in the life to come, which is the guerdon reſerued for him. But howe great the firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is, and howe many ſwéete ſolaces it conteyneth, no man knoweth, but he that hath read the Scriptures dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, which inculketh and repeateth
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150700:39"/>nothing more then the ſingular prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiues which our Lorde hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to his ſeruaunts in this life. Reade the holy Pſalme of the Prophet,
<note place="margin">Pſal 25. Pſal. 91. Pſal. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus regit me:</hi> Reade, <hi>Qui habitat in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intorio:</hi> Regarde with thy vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <hi>Diligam te domine fortitudo mea:</hi> reade the benedictions and the curſes of <hi>Deuteronomium:</hi> finally, reade the new and old Teſtament, and thou ſhalt ſée apparantly, what fauour and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is promiſed to the iuſt and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in this life. Heare the verdit of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> in his Prouerbes vpon this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Bleſſed is the man that hath found wiſedome, for it auayleth more to-poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe that, then all the heapes of golde and ſiluer, be it neuer ſo fine and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: it is of greater price then all the riches of the world: and all that can be wiſhed for, and deſired in the heart of man, is nothing comparable therevnto. The length of his daies are in his right hand, and in his left, are riches and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: his wayes are faire, and his pathes peaceable, and to all them that obtaine
<pb facs="tcp:150700:40"/>it, and to euery one that with perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce ſhall enioy it, ſhall be happie. Marke then, my ſonne, the conſtitutions and counſailes of God, for this ſhall be likings and life to thy ſoule. Then ſhalt thou take thy iourney voyde of care, and thy feete ſhall not fayle thée: if thou ſléepe, thou ſhalt not be affrighted: and if thou betake thée to reſt, thou ſhalt haue a quiet repoſe. This (deare brother) is the ſolace and quietneſſe that the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous haue in their wayes: but conſider howe much the wayes of the wicked differeth from this by the ſentence of the Scriptures: vnhappineſſe, and luckleſſe chaunce is euer in their way, neyther know they what it is to tread the ſteps of peace and tranquilitie. And againe, <hi>Eccleſiaſtick</hi> ſayth: The path of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt is ful of lets and obſtacles, and at the ende of their iourney for an harbour is addreſſed for them, hell, darkeneſſe, and paine. Doth it ſéeme now good vnto thée to diuert from the way of God, to follow the way of the world, béeing ſo contrary each to other, not onely in the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150700:40"/>and, but alſo in the midway, and at eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtep? Which then is the greater in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience, to endeuour through one torment to get another torment, or elſe with one repoſe to atchieue an other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? But that thou mayeſt diſcerne more clearely the manifolde benefites which preſently doo accompanie this good thing, bee attentiue to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe that GOD himſelfe made to the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> to the obſeruers of his commaundements, in theſe woordes, according to the intent of diuers In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters: When thou ſhalt be (ſayth hée) ſuch and ſuch, as I haue willed thée to be, vnwares ſhall come vpon thée the dawne of bright day (that is the light of iuſtice) which ſhall caſt out and banniſh quite the dryerie darkneſſe of thy errours and defaultes, and ſhalt quickely knowe true health, and the equitie of thy well dooings ſhall ſtande before thée as a burning lampe, and the glory of our Lord, ſhall enuiron thée on euery ſide, that thou mayeſt be honoured in the ſight of God,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:41"/>and men. Then ſhalt thou call vpon the name of our Lorde, and he will heare thée, becauſe thou louedſt him, and ſhall ſay vnto thée, behold me here preſt to accompliſh whatſoeuer thou canſt aſke. Then in the middeſt and déepe darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the tribulation and diſtreſſe of this life, the comfortable beames of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine fauour ſhall ſhine vpon thée, and thy tribulation ſhall be as the middeſt of the day, for that our Lord had ordeyned, that thy miſeries themſelues, and thy tranſgreſſions paſſed, ſhould accumulat vnto thée greater felicitie, preſenting alwayes to thy minde aſſured peace, and firme tranquilitie. And in the time of ſcarcitie and famine, he ſhall féede thee full, and ſhall ſupply thy wantes aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dauntly, and thy bones ſhall be deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from death, and from the flames of eternall fire, and thou ſhalt be like vnto a moyſt garden, and as a fountaine which runneth inceſſantly: and in thée, that ſhall be accompliſhed which many yeares hath bene vnfiniſhed, to the ende thou maieſt ſtand vpon a ſure founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150700:41"/>from generation to generation, and if thou wilt endeuour to celebrate my feſtiuall daies, not contriuing them in fooliſh delightes, nor in preferring thy will before mine, obſeruing careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly my will and beheſt in this voyage: then will I create thée a Lord, and will giue thée ſuch ſolaces as ſhall farre ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe all pleaſures of the worlde. And I will exalt thée aboue the higheſt turrets of the earth, to a moſt bleſſed ſtate of life, wherevnto neither fortune nor hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine nature can adde or detract ought at all. And after all this, I wil enſtal thée into the precious inheritaunce that I promiſed to <hi>Iacob</hi> thy father, which is the benediction of glorie, becauſe the mouth of God hath ſpoken it. Theſe are the rewards which God promiſed to his ſeruantes, of which although ſome are yet to come, notwithſtanding many of them pertaine to this preſent life. As is that new light and heauenly bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that abundance of all things, that aſſured truſt in GOD, that diuine aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to al petitions and demands, that
<pb facs="tcp:150700:42"/>peace and ſecuritie of conſcience, that diuine prouidence and protection, that flouriſhing Gardein (which is the deo king and garniſhment of grace) the fountaine which floweth continually, which is the great plentie of all things, thoſe ſupernall ioyes which excéede the capacitie of man, that lifting vp of the ſpirite which cannot be augmented by aſſiſtance of humane nature.</p>
               <p>Theſe fauours and prerogatiues pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by God, are all the workes of his mercy, the influence of his grace, the teſtimonies of his loue, the effect of the fatherly prouidence he extendeth to his ſeruaunts. Vpon euery one of theſe I could ſay much more then the breuitie of this volume will permit, for that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them would aſke a ſeuerall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. Wherefore the iuſt ſhall reioyce of all theſe good thinges, both in this life, and in the life to come, whereof the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt ſhall be vtterly deſtitute. By which meanes, marke what oddes is betwixt the one part and the other, nowe that theſe are ſo fauoured from heauen, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150700:42"/>thoſe in ſuch diſtreſſe and penury, for if thou conſider aduiſedly all things before treated of, &amp; doeſt weigh the eſtate and condition both of the iuſt and vniuſt, thou ſhalt finde that the lot of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous is in the fauour of God, but that of the vngodly in vtter diſgrace:
<note place="margin">The eſtate of the good and of the euill.</note> theſe are his friendes, the other his profeſſed foes: theſe enioy the light, the other dwell in darkneſſe: theſe participate in delight with Angels, thoſe with dririe ſwine: theſe are frée indeed, and maſters of themſelues, thoſe other the thrals and vaſſalls of Satan: theſe liue in vnitie, thoſe other in deadly diſcord: the truſt and teſtimonie of a falſe conſcience, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth theſe, and to the other mindes, reſorteth alwayes the guilt of their fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy facts: theſe with a reſolute minde abide the brunt of tribulation in their accuſtomed place, thoſe other, as light chaffe are repelled by the winde: theſe depende vpon the anker of hope, thoſe other haue no ſtay to leane vnto, being obiected to euery chaunce and chaunge of fickle fortune: the prayers of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:150700:43"/>are acceptable to the eares of the Lord, the other petitions are odious and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable. The death of theſe is quiet and glorious with diuine honour, and that of the others troubleſome, defamed, fraught with a thouſand feares. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, theſe liue as children vnder the guard and gouernment of God, they ſléepe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely vnder the winges and ſhadow of his prouidence: but the others exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from this diuine protection, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der too and fro as ſcattered beaſts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out head or guide, thruſt out to apparant perils and alaroms of fortune. Then if ſuch and ſo excellent perfections doo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company vertue, what reſtraynt can there be, why thou ſhouldeſt not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace ſo ſoueraigne a thing? what canſt thou alleage for thy excuſe herein? To wrangle and ſay, this is not true, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not extenuate thy guilt, ſéeing thou ſeeſt howe it is founded vppon the infallible word of God, and teſtimonies of the ſcripture. To ſay theſe perfections are of ſmall price, auayleth not, for that (as I haue before mentioned) they excéede
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150700:43"/>all that mans heart can wiſh for. To al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage that thou art thine owne enemie herein, and that thou doeſt not deſire theſe good things, is moſt vntrue: for a man is by nature a friende to himſelfe, and humaine will hath felicitie for his ſubiect, which is the ende of his deſires. To affirme that thou haſt no ſence nor taſte hereof, ſufficeth not to acquite thy crime, conſidering thou beléeueſt them to be true, although thou canſt not taſte them. Originall ſinne bereaued thée of thy taſte herein, but not of thy faith, and faith is a teſtimonie more ſure, more ſecure, and more doubtleſſe, then all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther experiences, witneſſes, and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants of the worlde. Wherefore then doeſt thou not preferre this teſtimonie before all the other allegations? Why doeſt thou not attribute more to fayth, then to thine owne ſottiſh ſéeming and iudgement? O that thou wouldeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminately commit thy ſelfe into the handes and armes of God, and truſt to him onely, how ſuddenly ſhouldeſt thou perceiue in thy ſelfe the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:150700:44"/>of theſe propheſies, ſhouldeſt ſoone ſee the greatneſſe of theſe treaſures, ſhouldeſt ſée how ſenſleſſe and blinde all worldlings are, which doo neither féele nor fancy this felicitie, and ſhouldeſt ſée with howe iuſt reaſon God commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs this kinde of life, ſaying, Come vnto me al ye that are laden and weary, and I will eaſe your gréefe. Receiue my yoke vppon you, and then ye ſhall finde comfort in your ſoules, for it is full ſwéete and delectable. God is no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuer, his promiſes are neither falſe nor fraudulent. Which ſith it is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed, why doeſt thou flée or faynt? why doeſt thou abandon peace and pleaſure? Wherefore deſpiſeſt thou the allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and ſwéete ſoundes of thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor? How dareſt thou to chaſe vertue from thée, hauing ſuch a gallant ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, as héere thou ſeeſt grauen by the hande of God? It was much leſſe then this, that Quéene <hi>Sabba</hi> had heard of <hi>Salomon,</hi> and yet ſhe came from the vttermoſt partes of the earth, to trie whether thoſe things were true
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150700:44"/>which were reported vnto her. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then hearing ſuch and ſo certaine tydings of vertue, doeſt thou not betake thée to a litle trauell? If thou wilt be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured hereof, graunt thy ſelfe vnto the word of God, and confidently commit thy ſelfe into his handes, looſe thy ſelfe from the hands which hath wrapt and wonne thée, and thou ſhalt ſée that the ſame of vertue is leſſe then her merite, and that whatſoeuer we haue ſaid is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, in compariſon of that ſhe is in her proper effect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To perſeuere in ſinne, with a thouſand excuſes and delaies; intending to amend his life hereafter, deceiueth a Christian mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uellouſly. For by this meanes he blindeth and burieth himſelfe in the durtie dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill of vice, and waxeth daily more prone therevnto, in ſuch wiſe, that iniquitie ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king deep roote in the intrailes of his mind, it will very hardly be remoued.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:150700:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>NOtwithſtanding all theſe aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s whereby the condition of vertue is iuſtified ſufficiently, the wicked wil neuer want their wonted excuſes and delaies: for as it is written, He that will ſhake off his friend, ſearcheth for a cauſe of quarrell, but in ſo dooing, he meriteth a gréeuous reprehenſion and control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Yet ſome there be which with one onely worde will eaſily reply to all this, ſaying, It ſufficeth them to amend hereafter, and then to reduce the courſe of their life to a better order: fooliſhly feyning to themſelues, that it is too hard a matter preſently for them ſo to doo, and that in time to come, they may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt &amp; atchieue this thing with more facilitie:
<note place="margin">How fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth himſelfe.</note> which is one of the groſſeſt errours wherewith a man may delude himſelfe. For if thou mindeſt ſo long to procéede and perſeuere in that peril<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous path wherein thou art entred, ſtill augmenting the heape of thine iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, howe canſt thou ſo eaſily hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150700:45"/>forſake it at thy pleaſure, thy naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie conditions béeing growne by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall cuſtome into an habite? Further, if thou continue héerein, euill cuſtome ſhall bee more fortified and confirmed, and nature ſhall be corrupted the more, and the diuell ſhall preuaile and haue more power vpon thée, and ſhalt be ſtill farther from the fauour of GOD, and conſequently more blinde, more encli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and plunged déeper in the ſtinking puddle of iniquitie. Then howe can it be more eaſie for thée to performe this buſineſſe, béeing increaſed with theſe newe difficulties, by reaſon of thy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeueraunce in ſinne. If euery time that thou doeſt offend, thou leaueſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a dayes iourney of thy voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age towardes vertue: how canſt thou more readily frame thy ſelfe thereunto hereafter, hauing let ſlip ſo many daies iourney, as thou haſt committed offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? It may well appeare, that by this anſwere thou art inſtructed by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of lyes and falſhood, that after thou haſt ſo long inured thy ſelfe to vice and
<pb facs="tcp:150700:46"/>folly, and haſte runned a race ſo farre from the trade of vertue, ſhall then bee moſt eaſie for thée to attayne therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. But among theſe things, what ſhall I ſay of the great power of cuſtome, and of the force ſhee hath to binde and wrap thée faſt in wickedneſſe? For true it is, that as they which faſten a nayle in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, with euery ſtroke they driue it further in, and yet with other ſtrokes further, and ſo the more ſtill they ſtrike, the more they faſten it, and waxeth thereby the more harde to pull out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: In like maner, by each euill fact we commit, vice, as it were with a bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, is more déepely rammed into our minde, where it is fixed ſo faſt, that there can very hardly bee founde any force able to remooue it. Whereby wée ſée not ſeldome, that the olde age of thoſe who in their flouriſhing yeares were wholely giuen to carnalitie, is often ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the diſſolute manners of theyr youth, yea although they then abhorre them, and nature thereof diſclaymeth vtterly: which onely commeth to paſſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150700:46"/>through the tyranny of euill cuſtome. For it is affirmed by <hi>Iob,</hi> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bones of the wicked, ſhall be full of thoſe vices that they vſed in their youth, which ſhall acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany them in their graues, in ſuch ſort, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vice hath no other end then death, which is the diſſolution and extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all mortall things, which onely ſuffiſeth to redreſſe and cure it. And the cauſe hereof, is cuſtome co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed, which nowe is growne to nature. For vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious appetites, taking ſuch roote in the bones and bowels of their ſouls, is euen like vnto a ioynt ague, which hauing ſetled it ſelfe in the intrailes of a man. is become incurable. The very ſame thing is ſhewed by our Sauiour in the reſurrection of <hi>Lazarus,</hi> which had lien dead nowe foure daies, whome GOD called againe to life with ſuch vehement ſhrikes and cries: notwithſtanding hee raiſed many from death before, with ſuch falicitie, thereby to make it knowne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, what a wonder it was that God raiſed him againe, who foure dayes had béene dead and buried.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150700:47"/>
               <p>This long ſince, is eſpied to be in ſinne. For (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> openeth this place) of theſe foure dayes, the firſt is the delight we haue in ſinne: the ſecond is, the conſent of minde: the third, the accompliſhment in déede: the fourth, the perſeuerance in ſin: and he that is come to this point, is <hi>Lazarus</hi> lying dead foure dayes, who cannot be receiued but with the loud lamentations and teares of our Sauiour. If peraduenture this chaunce vnto thée (which very ſeldome hapneth to any) tell mee what lawe canſt thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge for thy leawdneſſe, that God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all worlds hauing loued and created thée, to inueſt thée with the glory of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall felicitie, wilt not conſume in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of him, who hath bin thy benefactor and friend ſo long, in this ſhort &amp; brickle life that thou enioyeſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Repentance ought not to be deferred to the end of life, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God doth ſeldome grant them his grace to dye well. For he
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150700:47"/>that hath lead a leaud life, hath commonly a worſe death: and ſo findeth a righteous recompence for his vniuſt deſerts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>BVt ſome there be ſo blinde &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that it ſuffiſeth them not to haue ſinned all their life paſſed, but they reſolue with themſelues wilfully to wallowe therein, vntill they ſenſibly féele themſelues aſſited with the very ſommons of death. O dreadfull time, full of perplexitie, what thinkeſt thou with this price to purchaſe the Kingdome of Heauen, and to merit the ſocietie and ſeate of Angels? Doeſt thou not ſée, that whatſoeuer is done at this time, is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie, and not will: is forced, and not frée: is conſtraint, and not conſent: is feare, and not friendſhip: yet it is loue, not the loue of God, but ſelfe loue, which ſhunneth naturally his owne annoy? Doeſt thou not perceiue, that theſe things are méere oppoſite to the rule of equitie, that thou hauing dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
<pb facs="tcp:150700:48"/>the whole tearme of thy life to deuotion of the diuell, wilt in the ende require to be rewarded of God? Doeſt thou not behold herein, euen that which the fiue fooliſh Virgins did prepare, whereof the Euangeliſt ſheweth, that they were making them readie, when they ſhoulde haue giuen vppe their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts? Therefore, how canſt thou expect any better ſucceſſe, then thou art admoniſhed by this example, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the ſelfeſame carefulneſſe? God is mightie, and can inſpire vpon vs true repentance when he liſt: but howe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it happeneth at this houre, and howe fewe they bee, which then repent hartily, aſke <hi>S. Auguſtine, S. Ambroſe,</hi> S. <hi>Gregory,</hi> and all other Saints, and thou ſhalt ſée howe preciſely and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulouſly they ſpeake in this matter, and thou ſhalt well perceiue what a madneſſe it is, ſo confidently to commit thy ſelfe to the mercie of a gulfe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſo many ſkilfull Pilots did paſſe, with ſuch great horrour and feare. To dye well, is a knowledge which ought to
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150700:48"/>be learned all the life before, for in the houre of death, the diſeaſed is cumbred with ſo many cares and gréefes, that hée hath no leyſure to learne to dye well. It is a generall rule, that as the life is of euery man, ſuch is his daath.
<note place="margin">The death of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to their life.</note> Whereby it followeth, that if the life bee miſchée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, the death is miſerable, except God for ſome ſpeciall purpoſe doth diſpoſe it otherwiſe. Theſe be not my words, but the Apoſtles ſayings: The ende of the vngodly, ſhall be like vnto their deſerts. For ſpeaking generally, neither doo we looke for a good euent of wicked be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings, nor of good attemptes, cuill happes. Reade ouer the whole Byble, and thou ſhalt not heare any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated ſo oft as this: What ſéede a man ſoweth, ſuch croppe ſhall he gather: and that in the extremitie of death, the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt ſhall reape the fruite of their tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels: and that God will impart to euery man according to his merits: and that the death of euery man, ſhall be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable to the life he hath lead: and that the iuſtice of the righteous man, ſhall be
<pb facs="tcp:150700:49"/>vppon his head, and the curſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly vpon his head, likewiſe with a thouſand ſuch like ſentences. If all the diuine ſcriptures might be powred out, to ſée what would iſſue thereof, ſcarce a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing would appeare more often to our view then this.</p>
               <p>Wherefore if thy workes be wicked, and thy life likewiſe, what other thing can we prognoſticate thereof, but that the ende will ſuccéede as the beginning and middle hath béene? What thing elſe ſhall we thinke him to gather in the other life, but corruption, who in this life hath ſowen nothing elſe but corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Peraduenture as our Sauiour ſaith, We may gather roſes of thornes, figges of furſe-buſhes, &amp;c. If the houſe of the wicked, as <hi>Salomon</hi> ſayth, decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth towards death, and his foote path leadeth directly to hell, what other port can bee expected after this nauigation, but euen ſuch an ende as where the wall or trée ſhall fall, which bendeth to one ſide, but in that part whither it howeth moſt. For he whoſe life, whoſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150700:49"/>dooings, whoſe thoughts hath bene their onely regard to hell, (for that they haue all deſerued it) where ſhall he ſettle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe after all this, but euen there right? where ſhall he haue his habitation, if not in outward darkeneſſe, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way walked in inward darkneſſe? how wouldeſt thou bring to paſſe, that in the ende of his iourney he ſhould arriue in heauen, which hath alwayes purſued the beaten pathe that lyeth ſtraight to hell?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wee ought not to abuſe the mercie of God, perſeuering in ſinne, vpon confidence thereof. For if Gods mercy can ſuffer ſo many Infidelles in the worlde, and in the Church ſo many wicked Christians, and that all thoſe ſhould be cast away quite: he will alſo ſuffer that euery one which ſtil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth in ſinne, ſhall periſh eternally.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>ANd if on the other ſide thou ſay, that great is the mercie of God, which dooth embolden thée in ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:150700:50"/>that continuing in thy naughtie life, are yet aſſured of thy ſaluation. But tell mee, how canſt thou offer greater ini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the mercy of God, then of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neuolence to take occaſion to diſpleaſe him? Who taught thee to argue in this ſort, that becauſe God is good and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, ſhou ſhouldeſt haue leaue to be vngracious, and to merit heauen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by? The holy Ghoſt neuer taught thée this kinde of reaſoning, but rather in this faſhion, That God being ſo good, ought to be honoured, obeyed, &amp; imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, aboue all other thinges: wherefore ſith God is pittifull, it is good reaſon, that in him I ſhoulde repoſe my whole truſt and conſidence that he will pardon my treipaſſes, bee they neuer ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, ſo that I deteſt them vtterly, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my ſelfe vnto him with a ſincere heart. But procéeding alwayes in ſinne, beléeue it well, hée will not abeare it, yea, hee will condemne thée and hate thée the more, whome hée ſuffereth ſo long. Thou canſt not gainſay me, that of an hundreth partes of the worlde,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150700:50"/>there is ſcarce one repleated with Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and that of ninetie and nine which abide in the worlde, none are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For as in the time of that great flood, none was ſaued out of the Arke of <hi>Noe,</hi> nor out of the houſe of <hi>Rubbe,</hi> none eſcaped of thoſe which dwelt in <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> ſo none can be ſaued out of the houſe of God, which it his church, euen that which wee call Chriſtianitie. Beholde in what pickle and perplexitie it ſtandeth in theſe dayes, and thou ſhalte finde for certaine, that in this whole myſticall bodie from toppe to toe, is ſcarce any thing entire and ſounde. Sette aparte ſome principall Cittie where diſcipline taketh place, and range abroad through all Townes and other places, where (as I ſaide) is no talke of diſcipline, and thou ſhalte finde much people, of whome may be veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that which GOD ſaide touching <hi>Hieruſalem:</hi> Search all the ſtréetes and houſes of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and if thou ſhalte finde one iuſt man, for his ſake I will haue compaſſion vpon the Cittie.
<pb facs="tcp:150700:51"/>Raunge abroad (I ſay not now through Innes and Markets, for that theſe an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> places dedicated to deceit) but through the beſt Cittizens houſes. As <hi>Ieremie</hi> ſaith, Liſten thy eares to that they ſpeake, and thou ſhalt hardly heare ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> good word, but bitter backbytings and murmure ſhall fill thy eares. Their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, their oathes, their blaſphemie, laughter, diſcorde, threates, and of all ſides, both heart and tongues, debate of earthly droſſe and gaine, but verie ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God and good things, but alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither in ſwearing and forſwearing his holy name, which is the memory he hath left vnto vs. The ſame Prophet ſaying, Let them be mindfull of me, but not in ſwearing falſly by my name, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch ſort, that by the externall ſhewe, a man can ſcarce coniecture whether that nation be Chriſtian or Heathen, except it be by the ſounde of belles, and ruthful rage of ſwearing &amp; forſwearing, which ringeth rounde about, wherein they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céede all Infidels. Then how can the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bee vnited to the number of thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150700:51"/>whom <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaketh in this wiſe, All they that behold this people, ſhall quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowe them to bee the plantes to whom God gaue his benedictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ſuche ought to bee the life of a Chriſtian, that all they whiche beholde him, may ſoone iudge him ſo be the ſonne of God, in what ſort ſhall we déeme of thoſe which ſéeme rather ſcoffers and contemners of Chriſt, then Chriſtians indéed? If this then be the life of theſe, what hope can we haue of their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to the generall rule we haue ſet downe before? All this is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that thou maieſt perceiue, if God, notwithſtanding his ſo great mercie that thou alledgeſt, ſuffereth ſo many Infidels in the world, and ſo many euill Chriſtians in the church, and if all theſe Infidels doo periſh, and ſo many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians too, he will alſo be contented that thou ſhalt periſh with them, if thy life be conformable to theirs. But perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture the heauens were fauourable to thy birth, and therewith all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of God were altered,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:52"/>and the lawe of his Goſpell and of his iuſtice, that for thy ſake ſhould me made an innouation of all things. With this pittie he ſuffered the fall of Angels, and the tranſgreſſion of our firſt Parentes, and with them the blot of humaine ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and deſtruction of the whole worlde, with the great floud, and the dreadfull deſolation of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> of <hi>Niniuie,</hi> and of many other noble Cities and Prouinces.</p>
               <p>And with this, he ſuffred alſo that hell ſhould bee enlarged, and that daily ſo many millions of ſoules ſhould tumble thither: And will he not ſuffer likewiſe that thine ſhall paſſe the ſame way, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing as diſorderly as they did before thée? But thou maieſt obiect, that then God was rigorous, and is become now more milde and curteous, and yet with this pitie &amp; clemenſie, he hath ſuffered all that thou haſt heard, to the end that thou ſhouldeſt likewiſe feare thy fall, although thou be a Chriſtian, whileſt thou art wicked. Sith it is certaine, that fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe faith is not the inſtrument of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150700:52"/>but the chéefeſt matter of ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauate damnation. Perchaunce Gods glorie ſhall be leſſened if thou enter not therein, Or art thou of ſuch power, that God ſtandeth in néede of thée, and muſt heare with thée perforce? Or haſt thou any bill of his hande, whereby hée is hound to beſtow vpon thée ſuch paſſing priuiledges? If the children of <hi>Dauid</hi> which were priuiledged by the merite of their parents, God did not ſpare to puniſh them according to their deſerts, for that they offended gréeuouſly in his ſight, ſo that many of them died miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly in his diſgrace: whence haſt thou this confidence ſo to aſſure thy ſelfe of thy ſafetie? Thou doeſt ere, deare bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yea thou offendeſt, if thou take this to be truſt &amp; hope in God: this is not hope, but plaine preſumption: for that which we call hope, is, to beleeue that a man repenting &amp; forſaking ſin, God will forgiue him all his gréeuous crimes: but thine is preſumption, if thou beléeueſt, that perſiſting ſtill in wickedneſſe, ſhalt not faile of thy ſaluation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:150700:53"/>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To ſay that the loue of the world is the cauſe of ſinne, is a vaine excuſe, proceeding from a corrupt and carnall Chriſtian, who hath no taſte nor ſent of ſupernall bliſſe. Wherefore hee abiecteth thoſe which are true and ſincere, and ſearcheth buſily after falſe, fraile, &amp; momentall pleaſures, which preſently he perceiueth not. Then ſhould he knowe the deceit and daunger of them, and how perfect good are the ſpirituall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. XI.</head>
               <p>BUt perhaps thou wilt ſay, that the loue of the world hath thy heart and hands faſt hardle with the fetters of her ſlouriſhing vanities, and that ſhe it is that maketh thée to decline from thy well attempted voyage. This is the excuſe of one that hath not taſted of the ſpirituall delights, and therefore deſireth corporall comfort. The countrey clowne déemeth that there is no brauer Palace any where, then his rude Cottage at home, for that he neuer ſawe the lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150700:53"/>furreſs and curious workemanſhippe of Caſtles and Cities. The litle babe wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully wéepeth being deſcended from his mothers womb, becauſe he is ignoraunt yet howe much this worlde is better whither he commeth to dwell, then the priſon where he was pent before. Our firſt parentes made great reckonings of their villages and houſes made with ſtrawe, before they eſpied the braue buildings framed with timber &amp; ſtone. To whome wee may well reſemble all ſenſuall men, who hauing yet no taſte of ſpirituall ſpices, nor prooued their ſap, their ſwéetneſſe, their beautie, dignitie, and nobilitie, couet more gréedily the ſhadowes and ſhewes of happineſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they knowe not any part of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felt ſelicitie indéede. For if they had any true knowledge hereof, it were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible but that they ſhould vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe all ſenſuall ſolace. According to this ſaying of the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> In that day thou ſhalt deteſt all ſiluer and golde, and the idols which earſt thou diddeſt adore, euen as durtie ragges of no reputation,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:54"/>and ſhalt ſay vnto them, when thou art clenſed: Depart from me, get you out of my houſe, in ſuch ſort, as men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne their falſe gods, after they know the omnipotent God: So will they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect the vanities of the worlde, ſo ſoone as they haue a ſmacke of the true cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall bliſſe. For (as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith) at the firſt taſte of ſpirituall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, all fleſh from whence iſſueth each earthly delight, léeſeth his ſent. For this is that Syren ſong, that dreame of <hi>Sirces,</hi> which hath bewitched ſo many foretches. But in opening this deceit, mother fraude that lurked earſt, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in ſight, which is, that they are not onely ignoraunt of the ſpirituall bliſſe, but alſo of the temporall ioyes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for if they knew them through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is not poſſible that they ſhoulde like them ſo well as they doo. For tell me, what is the world and all the iolitie thereof, (if with in corrupt eyes ye rightly regarde it, his guiſe, his begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and progreſſe) what is this world I ſay, other then a heape of wo, a ſchoole
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150700:54"/>of vanitie, a market of deceit, a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit of errours, a priſon of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, alwaies infeſted with théeues, a durtie dunghill, a ſea of ſtormy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles? This world (as the Philoſopher ſaid) is a barren lande, a ſtormie field, a wood of thornes, a gréene medowe, full of ſerpents, a gallant garden, but fruitleſſe vtterly, a fountaine of vaine thoughts, a pleaſaunt poyſon, a fable finely framed, a delighting frenzie: what good things are therein, which bee not altogither falſe and frayle, and what euill things are incident to it, which bee not tryed to be true? his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is reſtleſſe, his ſecuritie without ſafetie, his paines to no purpoſe, his teares auaileth not, his intent without euent, his hope fruſtrate, his mirth fat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and forced: his dolours to bee true, is order full of diſorder and confuſion. So that deare brother, take it for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned veritie, that the quiet and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment which thou expecteſt, cannot bee had in this world, but to bee rich in the fauour of God, but in contemning
<pb facs="tcp:150700:55"/>thereof, and in eſtéeming leſſe of earthly things then they be indeede. Go rounde about the ſea and land, wander whither thou wilt (as ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) &amp; thou ſhalt finde wretchedneſſe euery where, if thou walk not in the way of the Lord, in whom conſiſteth all felicitie and content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The way of God is now nothing difficult, nor auſtere at all, but is become very plain and eaſie, by the inſtruction and enſample of Chriſt, but especially by his paſſion, his reſurrection, and aſſention, and after by his ſending downe of the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. XII.</head>
               <p>OTher there be which excuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſaying: The way of God is very hard, and this is onely becauſe his precepts are repugnant to the inclinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mans appetites. This is one of the principall cauſes that maketh men to loath this labour, but the authors of ſuch
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150700:55"/>allegations, though they bee Chriſtians, and liue vnder the lawe of grace, they knowe not yet the firſt letter that ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the Alphabet of this lawe, nor haue any ſmacke of this miſterie. O thou vnhappie wretche which makeſt profeſſion to bee a Chriſtian, tell mee I beſéech thée, wherefore came Chriſt into the world? wherefore did he ſhead his blood? why did he inſtitute ſo many ſacramentes? why ſent hee the holy Ghoſt? what is ment by the Goſpell, by grace, by this word Ieſu? what doth this renowmed name of Lorde and Sauiour ſignifie which thou woorſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt? If thou knoweſt not, aſke of the Euangeliſt, who ſayth: His name ſhall be Ieſu, for it ſhall be hée that ſhall ſaue his people from their ſinne. But what is it to be a ſauiour and deliuerer from ſinne, if by him wee doo not meritte par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for our offences paſſed, and grace to excuſe thoſe that are to come? For what cauſe came Chriſt into the world, if not to helpe vs to ſaluation? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore dyed he vppon the Croſſe, if not to
<pb facs="tcp:150700:56"/>ſlay ſinne? why did he riſe againe after his death, if not to reuiue vs? Likewiſe, wherefore ſpent hee his blood, if not for a medicine able to heale thy feſtered woundes? wherefore ordained hee ſo many Sacraments, if not for a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall remedie againſt ſinne? what is ſhe chéefeſt fruite of his comming and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, if not to ſhewe vs thereby the way to Heauen, which before was auſtere and difficult?
<note place="margin">Eſai. 40.</note> As appeareth by <hi>Eſaias,</hi> where hée ſaith? At the comming of <hi>Moſſias,</hi> the crooked wayes ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſtraight, and the bitter paſſages pleaſaunt, large, and wide. Beſides all this, why did he ſend his holy Ghoſt, if not of fleſh to make thée ſpirituall? and wherefore did hee ſende it in the forme of fire, if not to the ende thou ſhouldeſt bee inflamed as fire, illuminated, forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and tranſformed into himſelfe, and ſhould drawe thée to heauen, whence he deſcended, that he might powre vppon thée the grace and vertue that floweth from him abundantly, thereby to lighten the heauie yoake of ſinne, &amp; to mittigate
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150700:56"/>the exerciſe of vertue, by reioyſing in aduerſity, by hope in perils, and by ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comming in temptations. This is the beginning, the middle, and ende of the Goſpell, that as one carnall man and a ſinner (which was <hi>Adam</hi>) made vs all earthly and ſinners: ſo an other man béeing celeſtiall and iuſt (deſcending from Heauen) made vs all celeſtiall and iuſt. What other thing did the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes write of? What other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes did the Prophet foreſpeake of? what elſe did the Apoſtles preache of? There is no other diuinitie but this: this is the woorde abreuiated: this God wrote vppon the earth: this is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation and abridgement heard by the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> which was verified by the ſequell of the great abundance of vertue and iuſtice, which came into the world immediately after.</p>
               <p>Then (deare brother) behaue thy ſelfe, as though thou wert newly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to chriſtianitie, and aſke of ſome ſkilfull Diuine, what thou art charged to doo by this thy Religion: of whome
<pb facs="tcp:150700:57"/>thou ſhalt receiue no other aunſwere, then that it behooueth thée to bee a good man: which to accompliſh, this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion giueth thée comfort and courage, and cauſeth the carnall man to become ſpirituall, giuing vnto him the holy Ghoſt, the better thereby to procéede in the promiſes. Surely it is a great ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, that thou bearing the name of a Chriſtian ſo many yeares, knoweſt not yet what difference is betwéene the written lawe and the lawe of grace.</p>
               <p>In this then conſiſteth the difference (ſith thou knoweſt it not) that lawe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned a man to bee iuſt, not furniſhing him with forces neceſſarie for that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployt, but this alſo chargeth vs to bee iuſt and good, giuing grace and abilitie to accompliſh this commaundement: therefore for this cauſe and no other, it is tearmed, the law of grace. That preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vs to battaile, without weapons to fight: willed vs to aſcend to Heauen, but gaue vs no ladders to climbe: pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to men that they ſhould bee ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, yet did it not inſpire them with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150700:57"/>the holy Ghoſt that they might be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. But now it is otherwiſe, for this lawe ceaſing, the other ſuccéeded, which farre excéeded it, by his merites, and by the ſacred blood of Chriſt. And yet as though the olde lawe were not extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, nor Chriſt come into the world, thou ſtandeſt Iewiſhly coniecturing, that of thy ſelfe thou art ſufficient to fulfill and execute this lawe, and ſo to be iuſtified. Wherefore euery one that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth this, ſhall perceiue appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly that many Authors agrée, that this way of the Lord is both ſwéete and ſowre.
<note place="margin">Pſal. 18.</note> For loue of the wordes iſſuing out of thy mouth, ſaith the Prophet, I trudge a iourney harde and vnſauery. I am delighted with thy Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as with the greateſt treaſures. For this way conteineth in it ſelfe both partes, that is, it is difficult and eaſie: difficult in reſpect of nature, eaſie in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of vertue and grace: in ſuche ſort, that which was harde by one reaſon, is light by another. As our Sauiour ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth when hée ſaid, That his yoke was
<pb facs="tcp:150700:58"/>eaſie, and his burthen pleaſaunt: for a yoke and burthen is all ene in ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But to ſay it was ſwéete, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the facilitie hée had in bearing it here, through the grace which was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto him: So that if thou demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, howe it is poſſible that béeing a yoke it ſhould be eaſie, ſéeing it is the propertie of a yoke to bee heauie and hatefull? Wherevnto it may be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that God doth quallifie the gréefe of thoſe that willingly ſubmitte them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the ſaide yoke, as he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed by the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> ſaying, I will bee as hée whiche looſeth the yoke, and as he that vnloadeth a mans necke from the weight thereof. What thing is more woorthie of admiration, then this, that a yoke is eaſie, and that by God it is made portable, for that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſupporteth the burthen? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then dooth it ſéeme a thing incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto thée, that this burthen ſhould be pleaſaunt, ſéeing God dooth helpe to ſuſtaine it? But wilt thou ſée both theſe contrarieties to concurre in one perſon?
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150700:58"/>Heart what Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaieth,
<note place="margin">Rom. 5.</note> We ſuffer aduerſitie in ſundrie ſortes, yet are we not impatient: wée liue in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme penurie, nor for this are we ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commed: wée abide perſecutions, yet are we not deſtitute: we are humbled, yet not confounded: oppreſſed euen to the earth, yet not reiected vtterly. Now regarde on the one ſide the loathſome loade of labours, and on the other ſide, the delight that is therin by the benefite of grace,
<note place="margin">Eſay 40.</note> which yet the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſheweth more manifeſtly, ſaying, They which truſt in the Lorde ſhall chaunge their ſtrength, ſhall ruime ſwiftly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſweating, ſhall goe ſtill and neuer be weary. Sée héere the yoke made ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie by the vertue of grace. Beholde the fury of the fleſhe abated and conuerted to the force of the ſpirite, or to tearme it more rightly, the might of men tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into ſtrength of God. Heare how the Prophet did not reſtraine himſelfe neither from labour, nor from reſt, nor from the commoditie he gat of the one and other, where he ſaide, They ranne,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:59"/>and it gréeueth them not, they went forth ſtill and were neuer weary.</p>
               <p>Wherefore welbeloued brother, thou oughteſt not to diuert from this way, though it ſéeme ſomewhat harde and ſowre, ſith God and his grace are thy guides therein. For it is no reaſon that nature ſhould more preuaile then grace, nor <hi>Adam</hi> to bee of more power then Chriſt, nor the diuell to be greater then God: nor yet the cuſtome and long vſe of euill, then the habit of vertue and well dooings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A man ſhould not prognoſticate his conuerſion to God, nor his repentance and auerſion from thoſe offences, whereby hee hath diſpleaſed the diuine maieſtie of God, and his neighbour: for the more he is ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and infected with the filth of vice, and the ſlower hee is in cleanſing and curing thereof, ſo much the more hee doth aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate the burthen of his penance.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:150700:59"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIII.</head>
               <p>WHerefore if the cauſes bee ſo many, and ſo great, which of the one part dooth moue thée to change the courſe of thy life to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter race, and on the other ſide, haue no ſufficient excuſe to withhold thée from ſo dooing: Tell me, I pray thée, when wilt thou be ready to reuolt from ſin? Turne back thy eye, brother, a litle, towards the life that is paſſed, and conſider of what yéeres thou art now: for now is the time, for the houre of enterance is paſſed, and the beginning to vnloade thy ſelfe from thy former faultes. Beholde that thou being a Chriſtian, regenerate with the water of holy baptiſme, hauing God for thy father, and the Church for thy mother, which God formed and framed with the lawe of his Goſpell, and with the doctrine of the Apoſtles and Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, and (that more importeth) with the foode of Angels, and yet thou liueſt ſo looſely as thou were an Infidell alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither, and neuer kneweſt God. But
<pb facs="tcp:150700:60"/>tell me, what ſort of ſinne, what follie can bee founde, wherein thou art not culpable? what forbidden trée is there, wherein thou haſt not fixed thy eyes? what gréene medowe, where at leaſt in thought thou haſt not glutted thy laſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciuious luſt? what pleaſaunt accident hath béene obiected to thy ſight, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto thy deſire hath not bene extended? What appetite of thine haſte thou not aſſayed to accompliſh? Calling God to thy minde, and how thou art a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, what more couldeſt thou doo, then to haue a fayth without expectation of the other life, and feare of future iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? What hath thy life bene elſe then a webbe of wickedneſſe, a ſinke of ſinne, a pathe of pleaſure, a perpetuall diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God? How haſt thou ledde thy life hitherto, but as thy appetites hath guided thée, as beſt fancied thy fleſhe, in exalting thy ſelfe, and in the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the worlde? Theſe haue béene thy Goddes, theſe the Idols wherevnto thou haſte kneeled and crowched, whoſe heſtes thou haſte fully perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150700:60"/>But in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meane time, what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count haſte thou kept with the diuine lawe of God, and thy allegeaunce due vnto him? Perchaunce thou haſt eſtée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med him no more then if hée had bene a God made of wood, for many Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians there bee, which will as eaſily beléeue that there is no God, as they thinke to offende him ſcotfrée. For they doo no leſſe beléeuing the one, then they woulde if they beléeued the other. What greater wrong, what greater deſpite may there bee, to ſo greate a Prince, then thou beléeuing all that the Chriſtian religion inſtructeth thée, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt no otherwiſe then if it were a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble? But art thou not appalled at the multitude of thy former offences, done without gruge of conſcience? Dooth not his omnipotencie cauſe thee to quake, againſt whome thou haſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted ſuch enormous crimes? Lift vp thy eyes, and regard the immeaſurable greatneſſe of that ſupernall Lorde, ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of all the Potentates of Heauen, before whome the whole circuite of
<pb facs="tcp:150700:61"/>the world lyeth proſtrate, in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, all that is created is as light chaffe toſſed with euery puffe of winde. And conſider what a thing it is, that ſuch a ſilly worme as thou art, haſt ſo oft pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noked the wrath of that eternall God. Looke vppon the excéeding greatneſſe of his iuſtice, and the ſharpe puniſhments which hitherto he hath vſed in the world againſt ſinne, not onely in particular perſons, but in Citties, Nations, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, Prouinces, and in the vniuerſall world: and not only in the earth, but in heauen, and there not in ſinners only, but in his owne innocent ſonne. Then if this were executed vpon gréene wood, and for the faultes of others, what ſhall be done in withered wood ouercharged with the weight of proper offences.</p>
               <p>Wherfore what can be more vndecent and intollerable, then that ſuche a vile vermine ſhould delude a Lorde ſo puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt, that with a becke or a word can detrude thée into the deapth of hell and damnation. Looke in like ſort vpon the patience of this Lorde, who nowe ſo
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150700:61"/>long hath looked for thy returne, as thou haſt béene an offendour. If after ſo long ſufferance, thou wilt ſtill abuſe this mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de in incenſing him to anger, hee will vnloade his bowe, will emptie his qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, and powre vppon thée the dartes of damnation. View the profoundneſſe of his déepe iudgements, whereof wee reade and ſée daylie things worthie to be wondred at. We may ſee a <hi>Salomon</hi> after all his wiſedome, his parables and profounde myſteries of the Cantickles, to forget God, and to fall downe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerence of Idols. We may ſée one of the firſt ſeuen Deacons of the Church, which were enſpired with the holy ghoſt, not onely became an heretick, but alſo a teacher, and a father of hereſie. Wee may ſée day by day many ſtarres to fall from Heauen into the earth, with a miſerable fall, to tumble in durt, and to bee fedde with the draffe of ſwine, which earſt at the table of our Lorde, were ſuſteined with the bread of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Therefore if the righteous for their ſecret pride, or negligence and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:62"/>became ſo vnmi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d full of God, after they had béene his dutifull Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts ſo many yeares: What doeſt thou looke for, hauing framed thy life to no other trade then to accumulate one ſinne vppon an other? Therefore, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſocuer we ſée to liue in this ſort (as wee haue tolde of before) ſhall it not bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, that hee ſhoulde nowe at the length, ceaſe to fill vppe the meaſure of his iniquities, and to aſſay to pleaſe God, and to deliuer his ſoule from bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage? ſhould it not ſuffiſe him, that he hath liued ſo leaudlie till this houre, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting himſelfe wholy to the worlde, the fleſh, and the diuell, and hereafter to imploy himſelfe, and to runne out the remnant of his race, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the homage and honour of God? is it not néedefull after ſo long time, and ſo many iniuries committed againſt his Diuine Maſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, to feare his ſeuere inſtice, which the more patiently it beareth with the wicked, ſo much the more rigorouſly is reuenged vppon them in the ende? ſhall it not be reaſon that hee ſhould bee
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150700:62"/>afraid to lye ſo long ſwallowed vppe in the gulfe of ſinne, depriued of the grace of God, and to haue ſo ſtrong an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie as is hee, who of a deare father, through his deſerts is become his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerſarie and his iudge? Shall it not bée reaſon, to dread, leaſt the force of long vſe bee turned into nature and habitte, making of vice neceſſitie? How ſhould hee not feare by little and little to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a reprobate ſence: whereunto when a man is come, hee doth not any thing that is acceptable in the ſight of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God? The Patriarke <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid to his father in lawe <hi>Labin,</hi> Fourtéene yeares are paſſed ſince I haue ſcrued thée, and haue had charge of thy buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and now it is time that I attend vppon mine owne affaires, and that I begin to prouide for mine owne houſe.</p>
               <p>Wherefore I pray thée, ſith thou haſt bin ſo long, not a retayner, but a daylie waiter to the worlde, not letting ſlip any oportunitie of this life, which was eyther appendaunt to thy pleaſures, or agréeing to thy appetites: ſhall it
<pb facs="tcp:150700:63"/>not to be reaſonable for thée nowe at the length, to get ſome commoditie for the ſoule, and for the bertering of thy eſtate, in the other life? certainly there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more ſhort and vnſure, then the life of man. Why then thou prouiding ſo carefully all neceſſaries for that which is ſo momentall and tranſitory, doſt not likewiſe make ſome prouiſion for that which endureth for euer?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A man ought to remember himſelfe, and that he is a Chriſtian, and that he beleeue firmely all that he is taught by his faith, which ſhould mooue him eyther through loue or feare. All things inuite him to the loue and ſeruice of God, among which hee ſhould acquire wiſedome, and harken to the words of Chriſt, who fixed himſelfe to the croſſe for our redemption.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. XIIII.</head>
               <p>NOw therfore if it be true as I haue ſaid, I beſéech thée deare brother, and charge thée by the precious blood of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150700:63"/>Chriſt, that thou remember thy ſelfe that thou art a Chriſtian, and that thou take all that which our faith teacheth for vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feined veritie, which plainly prooueth vnto thée, that beſides other things thou haſt a iudge, to whoſe eye lyeth open all the actions and moments of thy life, who will come at a day vnwares, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he will exact an account of thée, euen of euery idle worde. This faith telleth ſhée farther, that a man at his death, is not quite extinguiſhed, becauſe after this mortall life, ſuccéedeth an other, which laſteth eternally: and ſhat mens foules doo not periſh with their bodies, but that the bodies reſting, and raked vp in their graues, the ſoules yet enter into a newe Kingdome, and into an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther new world, where ſuch condition and company ſhal be aſſigned vnto them as their manner and behauiour hath bin in this life. Héere vnto this faith adioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth yet more, that as the rewarde of vertue, ſo the ſcourge of vice is ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, that although the whole worlde were full of bookes, and euery creature
<pb facs="tcp:150700:64"/>were a Scriuener, the writers woulde ſooner dye, and the world be at an ende, before it could bee knowne and treated of particularly, that which each of theſe doth containe in it ſelfe. This faith al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo informeth thée, that our debt and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is ſo great, through our benefites re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of God, that though the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of a mans yeares did ſurpaſſe the ſandes of the ſeas, yet they ſhould be too fewe to acquite himſelfe in his ſeruice towards him. The ſame faith affirmeth, that vertue is of ſuch paſſing valour, that all the treaſures of the worlde, and all that a mans heart can deſire, may in no reſpect be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared the reunto. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ſuch and ſo great things doo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort vs to vertue, why be there ſo fewe which imbrace it, and endeuour them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to attaine it? If men may bee mooued with any aduauntage or inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, what greater gaine is there? what life more perdurable? If with feare, what ſharper puniſhments? what paint more permanent? If with the bonds of bountious liberalitie, what greater
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150700:64"/>debt haue wee then that which we owe vnto God, of whom wee haue receiued all things? If the dread of dangers may ſtirre vs, what greater perill can there bee then that of death, whoſe comming is ſo vncertaine, whoſe account ſo ſtraight? If peace, if libertie, if the gifts of the holy Ghoſt, and the ſolace of a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gred life, be deſired of all men, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth euidently, that all theſe things are founde more readilie in that life which is lead by vertue and reaſon, then in that which is ruled by rage and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for that a man is a reaſonable creature, and not a beaſt. But if all this bee not regarded, ſhall it not bee ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, that for the maintenaunce of veriue, GOD deſcended from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the earth, and was made man, (who hauing created y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world in ſix dais) imployed thirtie and thrée yeares in this worke, wherein hee alſo ſpent his bloud and life. God dyed to ſlay ſinne, yet for all this, wee endeuour to reuiue in our hearts thoſe whom God would deſtroy with his owne death.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150700:65"/>
               <p>What ſhould I ſay more? for all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are ſufficient to promote this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or to ſhewe it as it is. Fo, I ſay, not reſpecting the croſſe onely, but which way ſoeuer we turne our eyes, we ſhall finde, that all things doo cry and cal vs to this commoditie, ſith there is no crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the world (if hee bee well noted) but doth inuite vs to the loue and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of our ſupernall Lord: in ſuch ſort, that looke howe many creatures there be in the world, ſo many preachers there are, ſo many bookes, ſo many voyces, which doo ſtirre vs therevnto. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, howe is it poſſible that ſo many ſhriking ſounds as héere thou heareſt, ſo many promiſes &amp; thundring threats, can beare no parte to perſwade thée thereunto? What ſhould God, or could he doo more then that he hath doone, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by promiſing or threatning, to drawe vs to himſelfe, and to withdraw and terrifie vs from ſinne? This not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, béeing of ſuch weight, what ſhal I blame the boldneſſe or blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſſe of men, which beléeuing this
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150700:65"/>aſſuredly, doubt not to dally out the day in ſinne, to ſléepe with ſinne, to ariſe with ſinne, and to bathe themſelues in the beaſtly puddle of all iniquities: and to doo all this without feare, without ſcruple, without abridging their ſléepe, or abating their fare, as though all their beléefe were a dreame, and the ſayings of the Euangeliſts, fables of <hi>Titius</hi> the Giaunt, and ſuch like? Howe couldeſt thou doo more then thou doeſt, if thou diddeſt doubt of thy beléefe? ſith it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that hitherto onely the ſhame and feare of the wordle hath brideled thy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petites: yet the feare of God cannot reſtraine thée from ſatiſfying thy ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualitie, nor make thée bluſh in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy diuelliſh deuices. Tell me, blind as thou art, depriued of vnderſtanding, béeing in ſuche ſecuritie and confidence, wherevpon worketh the worme of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? whither is fayth vaniſhed, knowledge, iudgement, reaſon, which onely endued thée with the title to bee called a man? Doeſt thou not dread ſo huge, ſo certaine, ſo vndoubted daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers?
<pb facs="tcp:150700:66"/>If thou were ſet at the table and ſerued with meates, and ſome man ſhould come vnto thée (thogh a knowne lyer) ſaying, that the meates ſet before thée were impoyſoned, thou wouldeſt doubt and dreade to cate it, were the meate neuer ſo delicate, and he a lyer that did aduiſe thée: Then if the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, if the Apoſtles, if the Euangeliſts, if God himſelfe doth cry vnto thée, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Death is in the potte, O wretched man, death dwelleth in gluttonie, which the diuel preſenteth before thée, and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt thou to receiue thy death with thy owne hands, and to drinke the dramme of thy damnation? What now auaileth this beléefe buried in thy boſome? where is his light, his firmneſſe as ſtéele, his pearſing ſharpeneſſe, ſéeing none of all theſe things can extenuate thy ſinne?</p>
               <p>O madde myſer, O franticke foole, made ſenceleſſe by the ſubtile ſleightes of the Serpent, adiudged to eternall darkeneſſe both within and without, for that thou goeſt ſtraight from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde to outward darkeneſſe. Blinde
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150700:66"/>thou art, becauſe thou ſeeſt not thy mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie: ſenceleſſe, becauſe thou doeſt not perceiue thy perdition: and more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate then the Diamonde, becauſe thou féeleſt not the weightie béetle of the worde of the Lorde. O wreche wrapte in woe tenne thouſande folde, woorthie to be bewayled with no other teares then thoſe whiche ſhall lament thy damnation, ſaying, If thou kneweſt the contentment, the quiet, the peace, and riches that God in this life hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vnto thée, which nowe are thus ſhut and kept from thée. O wretched was the diſmall day of thy natiuitie, but muche more miſerable ſhall bee the day of thy death, which ſhall be the verie doore and firſt ſteppe to thy damnation. Howe muche better had it beene, if thou haddeſt neuer béene borne, then to bee tormented for euer? Howe muche better had it béene for thée neuer to haue béene baptiſed, nor to haue knowne the fayth, ſithe there they ſerue thée to none other ende but to make thy faulte more gréeuous? for
<pb facs="tcp:150700:67"/>if the reache of reaſon bee ſufficient to cauſe the guilt of the Philoſophers to be inexcuſable, for that they knowing God in a ſort, did not glorifie him (as the Apoſtle ſaith.) Howe muche leſſe can he excuſe himſelfe whoſoeuer hée be, hauing receiued the light of faith, and the water of Baptiſme, and yearely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth the holy Communion, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day heareth his doctrine, doth nothing that belongeth therevnto, as the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers themſelues haue ſhewed to haue done in their liues? But what ſhall we inferre of all that we haue ſaid before, if not to conclude briefly, that there is no other fence, no other wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, no other counſell in the worlde, but to reiect all the lettes and intricate cares of this life, and to purſue that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pathe, where is obteyned ſure peace and eternall bliſſe? To this reaſon doth inuite vs, iuſtice, lawe, heauen, earth, hell, life, death, and the mercy of God. To this the holy Ghoſt doth enioyne vs by the mouth of <hi>Ecclaſiaſtick,</hi> ſaying, My ſonne, employ the flouriſhing yeres
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150700:67"/>of thy youth to diſcipline, that in thy age thou maiſt ſucke the ſwéete ſappe of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience, as he which tilleth and ſoweth, expecteth with patience the commoditie that groweth thereof. Thy griefe &amp; ſmart ſhal be very ſlender, and ſoone ſhalt haue a plentifull harueſt. My ſonne harken to my words, and deſpiſe not the aduiſe I giue thée: put voluntarily thy féete into the fetters, that prudence hath prepared, and thy neck into her yoke: bowe downe thy ſhoulders, and take her bonds vpon thée, and let it not gréeue thée to bee tyed therewith: Couple thy ſelfe to her with all thy heart, with al thy forces, and with all thy might: Follow her footeſteppes, ſearch her diligently, and thou ſhalt find her, and when thou haſt found her, léeſe her not againe in any condition. For ſhe ſhal giue comfort to thy crooked age, and that which earſt ſéemed ſowre and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous vnto thée, ſhall become ſwéete and delectable, and her fetters ſhall bee the foundation of vertue, and her chaines the iewels of glorie. For in that happie life, her bondes are the bulwarkes of
<pb facs="tcp:150700:68"/>health. Thus much ſaith <hi>Eccleſiaſtick,</hi> by which wordes hée notifieth vnto vs, the great beautie, the delights, the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie and riches of true wiſdom, which is vertue it ſelfe, and the knowledge of God, of which we héere treate. But if this be not ſuffient to mollifie thy ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie heart, lift vp thy eyes, and looke not to the water of the world, which fléeteth quickly, but beholde that Lord, who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vpon the Croſſe, and ſharpely ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying for that whiche thy ſinnes deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Where he ſtandeth in that forme as thou ſeeſt, with his féete faſtened, to ſtay for thée, and with his armes ſtretcht abroad to receiue thée, and with his head declining to giue thée at thy comming (as to the prodigall ſonne) the ſwéet kiſſe of reconciliation. There he calleth to thée (if thou haſt the grace to heare him) with ſo many cryes as he hath woundes in all his bodie. Imagine with thy ſelfe that thou heareſt his wordes in thy heart, ſounding in this ſort: Turne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, turne vnto me, O Samaritane, turne vnto me, for I will receiue thée.
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150700:68"/>Thou knoweſt well that thou haſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted adultery, with all thoſe louers thou luſteſt after, yet for all this turne vnto me, and I will pardon thée: turne vnto me, I ſay, for I am thy father, thy God, thy Creator, thy Sauior, thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friend, thy onely benefactor, thy full and perfect felicitie, thy finall ende. In me thou ſhalt find reſt, ioy, peace, health, truth, wiſedome, and all treaſures. In mée thou ſhalt finde the flowing vaine of the liuely water, which chaſeſt thirſt away, and lifteth vp a man to life eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. In me thou ſhalt ſtand like vnto the trée planted by the riuers ſide, which yéeldeth his fruite in due and conuenient time, whiche neuer léeſeth his verdure, and all that hée doeth ſhall ſuccéed pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperouſly.</p>
               <p>My brother, theſe are the voyces, the drums, and trumpets, wherewith Gods eternall wiſedome, calleth ſinners vnto him, if thou wilt harken to this harme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and not lyſten to the Syren ſonges of the ſubtil Serpent, turne thy ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:150700:69"/>to God, and amende thy life ſpéedily, to the which ende this Treatiſe is addreſſed. But how this is to be performed, ſhalbe ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in the next vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The ende of the Conuerſion of a Sinner.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="contemplations">
            <pb facs="tcp:150700:69"/>
            <head>Sundrie profitable Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations, gathered by the <hi>ſaide Author.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Christian man which couetteth to come vnto God, must make his enterance through the gate of compunction, general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſing all his offences. Wherevnto it ſhall auaile him much, to exerciſe himſelfe euery day in certaine Prayers and godlie Meditations, and in the conſiderations of death and of Gods ſeuere iudgement.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E therefore that is departed out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> and beginneth to march towards the land of promiſe: hee that like vnto the loſte ſonne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remembreth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and openeth his eyes to behold the beames of glittering vertue, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the perplexitie wherein hée is plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:70"/>and the fraude of this fraile life, and deſireth to returne to the plenteous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſtes of his fathers houſe, his firſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage muſt be through the ſtraights of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, where it behoueth him ruthfully to record in his minde the former ryots and exceſſes, and firmely to purpoſe the amendment of them. And for that this diſcuſſion and examination ought to bee as the Prophet ſayth, with affliction and remorce of conſcience, it is the part of the penitent, at that time to vſe al ſuch prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers &amp; ronſiderations as by any meanes may ſtir him to teares and dolour. To the which auaileth much the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of death, of Gods finall iudgement, of the paines of hell, and of the paſſion of Chriſt, ſuffered for the ſatiſfaction of our ſinnes: Sith it is apparant, that if there had bin no defects on our ſide, there had héene no cauſe of his gréeuous annoy. Theſe and ſuch like conſiderations may mooue vs to ſorrow, and to the deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſin, which is the chéefeſt part of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance. In the which we ſhould exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe our ſelues, not onely the ſpace of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150700:70"/>fiue or ſixe dayes, but the greateſt part of our life. Wherein many penitents are deceiued, who béeing moſt diligent in ſcouring their conſcience, and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their faultes, are quite careleſſe in bewayling of them, whereas both the one and the other are moſt neceſſarie, but chéefly the laſt. And I thinke veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the cauſe why ſo many faynte in the following of vertue, and in long time cannot attaine to perfection, and ſometime to ſurceaſe their iourney be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne, is, becauſe they haue not layde a ſure foundation, nor haue not plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the rootes déepe inough in this exerciſe. For this béeing the piller of all the building, when the foundation it ſelfe is féeble, the worke cannot bee firme which is erected vppon it. To the which ende, it is very neceſſarie to aſſigne certaine dayes, many or ſewe, as the holy ghoſt ſhall direct vs, wherein (as I haue ſayde before) we may exerciſe our ſelues in all ſuch prayers and meditations as maye induce vs to this ſorrowe. For the
<pb facs="tcp:150700:71"/>plainer declaration of this doctrine, I minde to impart vnto you a fewe of the foreſaid conſiderations, which may ſerue, not onely to ſtirre vs to be ſory for our ſinnes, and to the hatred thereof, but alſo to allure vs to the loue of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and to the feare of God, and to the contempt of the world, for al this is néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to nouices and beginners.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that liſt to encline his heart to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of ſinne, and to the dread of God, muſt conuey himſelfe into ſome couert corner, and muſt bend and imploy his minde to the contemplation of the heauenly bliſſe, and the iniquities which abound here in earth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>VVHoſoeuer then will haue his heart ſetled hereupon, and wil faſten this firmly in his mind, muſt eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day once or twiſe, take a time moſt quiet &amp; conuenient for that purpoſe, and ſequeſtring himſelfe into a ſecret place, al other earthly thoughts and vain ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations
<pb facs="tcp:150700:71"/>being laid apart, arming him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe firſt with the ſhield of faith, &amp; hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly crauing the grace of the holy ſpirit to aſſiſt him in this behalfe: aſſuming to himſelfe, the minde of that deuout Publican, which durſt not to lift vp his eyes towards Heauen, for the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and horrour of his offences. Let him repeate ſome generall confeſſion, or elſe the Pſalme <hi>Miſerere mei deus,</hi> with ſo great deuotion as he can deuiſe, and ſuddenly let him apply his minde to the conſiderations following, that by this meanes he may attain the feare of God, through the ſorrow, the dread, and dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration, a chriſtian ought to runne ouer the multitude of the mortal offences that he hath committed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <p>THe firſt ſting that may ſtirre vs to the woe and hatred of our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, is, to conſider the infinit
<pb facs="tcp:150700:72"/>number of them, and to fixe them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, as a terrible troupe of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Souldiers, that the ſoule may be appalled with ſo hidcous a ſpectacle. Runne ouer therefore bréefely all the commaundements of God, through all the capitall ſinnes, through all the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the powers and parts as well of thy body, as of thy ſoule, and thou ſhalt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, that there is ſcarce any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement which thou haſt not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed, nor any ſinne wherein thou haſte not ſunke, nor any ſence exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall or internall, which thou haſte not abuſed, nor any benefite which thou haſte imployed to that ende for which it was giuen thée: But as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet ſayth, God hath giuen thée his golde and ſiluer, and therewith thou haſte ſerued <hi>Baal.</hi> Looke therefore in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy ſelfe throughly, and viewe the race of thy life paſſed, and thou ſhalt ſée a huge webbe fraught full of deceit, of trecherie, of pride, of lyes, of ſlouth, of enuie, of couetouſneſſe, of hatred, of entiſements, of blaſphemie, of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150700:72"/>and of a thouſand other manners of miſchiefes: and thou ſhalt finde, that like a brutiſh beaſt, in all and euery of theſe thou haſte followed and fulfilled thy ſenſuall delights, without regarde of the lawe of iuſtice or reaſon, and thou ſhalt perceiue, that thou haſt liued as a Gentile or Pagan altogither, which neuer knewe God, or as though thou ſo beleeueſt, that there were no God, no death, no iudgement, no paine, no bliſſe, nor any thing elſe to be thought, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to be borne, and to dye. He then that hath liued this many yeares ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly, ſhall it not be reaſon, that he imploy the fewe dayes that are remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his life, in bewayling his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer yeares fondly conſumed, and to féele ſenſibly the ruine and decay of the powers of his ſoule, and the time that hee might hane gayned in this while, which hee ſhall not get hereafter? For time loſt can neuer be recouered.</p>
               <p>Throw therefore thy ſelfe downe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate before the feete of thy ſauionr, and with a pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiue hart, ſay as followeth. My
<pb facs="tcp:150700:73"/>ſinnes, O Lorde, are in number about the ſands of the Sea. I haue ſpotted my ſelfe with the filth of euery vice, and my offences are ſo multiplied, that I deſerue not, nor dare not to beholde the Heauens, becauſe I haue prouoked thy wrath, and haue done euill in thy ſight.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the ſecond conſideration he ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that by ſinne is loſt the grace &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of the holy Ghoſt, the mutuall amitie, the fauour &amp; fatherly protection of God, the participation of all the good things don in the vniuerſall Church, and the benefit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of Chriſtes paſſion.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. IIII.</head>
               <p>VVEigh farther, of howe great treaſures vice doth robbe and ſpoyle thée, which is one of the conſiderations that ſhoulde moſt affright a Chriſtian, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hee bee, examining throughly on the one ſide, what is loſt by ſinne, and on the other ſide, with what facility care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe men offend daylie. For by ſinne is
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150700:73"/>loſt the grace of the holy Ghoſt, which is the moſt precious gift that God can beſtowe vppon his beſt beloued in this life. It robbeth vs alſo of the fauour of God, which alwayes accompanieth his grace. And if it be a great griefe to léeſe the fauour of an earthly Prince, howe muche greater ſhould the griefe be, to incurre the diſpleaſure of him that is king of heauen and earth? It bereaueth vs of the vertuous flowing from aboue, of the giftes of the holy Ghoſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the ſoule is made bright and pure in the ſight of God, and is armed and animated againſt the force and violence of the enemie. It robbeth the ſoule of his intereſt in heauen, which procéedeth from the ſame grace, ſith that by grace glory is giuen (as the Apoſtle ſaith.) Alſo of the ſpirit of adoption, which maketh vs the ſonnes of God, and inſtéed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, inſecteth vs with the furie of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which cauſeth vs to impugne his holy pleaſure, whereby wée léeſe the entertainment due vnto ſonnes, and the fatherly prouidence which God ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb facs="tcp:150700:74"/>of thoſe whome hée receiueth for his children, which is one of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt treaſures that in this life may bee enioyed. Wherein the Prophet reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced not without good cauſe, when hée ſaide, I am right glad (O Lorde) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſée my ſelfe ſhrowded vnder the ſhadowe of thy winges, which is, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection and fatherly proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that he hath of his choſen people. By ſinne, is loſt, the peace, the quiet, and comfort of a guiltleſſe conſcience, the ſwéeteneſſe and ſolace of the holie Ghoſt, the fruite and merite of the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous actions that thou haſte wrought all thy life before, euen vntill that houre, the participation of all thoſe treaſures which the Church holdeth in her cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Finally, by ſinne is loſt the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation and fruition of the merites which flowe from Chriſtes paſſion, who is our head, becauſe a ſinner is not incorporated in his bodie as a liuely member through grace and charitie. All this is loſt by one mortall offence, and that which is gained thereby, is, to be
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150700:74"/>adiudged to eternall tormentes, and for that time to be cancelled out of the booke of life, and in ſteade of the ſonne of God, to bee made the vaſſall and bondſlaue of Sathan: and in ſteade of the temple and ſeate of the moſte bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Trinitie, to become the denne of théeues, the neaſt of Serpents, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt and harbour of venemous Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filiſkes. This is the guerdon conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient for ſinne, whereby thou maieſt learne, whether it bee not good reaſon to tremble and quake, beholding with howe little ſcruple of conſcience, with what facilitie and confidence, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny careleſſe men offende without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And farther, what reaſon it were that thou bedeaweſt thy chéekes with bloudie teares, if not for the loue of God, yet at leaſt for thine owne diſtreſſe, which haſt loſte ſuche ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable riches, for ſo ſmall a myte as is the delight and taſte of one treſpaſſe. If <hi>Eſau</hi> wayled and wept ſo bitterly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had loſt his inheritance in lewe of the like taſte: with what cryes and
<pb facs="tcp:150700:75"/>complaintes ſhouldeſt thou fill heauen and earth, for the loſſe of ſo woorthie of patrimonie? that with gréefe and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes ſharpe, thou maieſt recouer the thing thou haſt loſt by dalliance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the third conſideration, hee ſhould thinke vpon Gods benefites beſtowed vpon man, that he might be abaſhed therat, and be aſhamed of himſelfe. And therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne himſelfe to ſome ſharpe affliction, for that hee hath bene a creature ſo vngrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnkinde.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <p>FOr the better replication of this, pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in thy minde the infinit number of Gods benefites. For how much the more a man wayeth how bountifull God hath bene towardes him: ſo much the more he ſhall be confounded in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſéeing how wicked he hath ſhewed himſelfe to God. In this ſort the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets did often perſwade the people of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150700:75"/>God to repentance. And in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet beganne with <hi>Dauid,</hi> when ere he reprooued him of adultery, laide before him the fauoure and regall dignitie, wherevnto God had promoted him, and what elſe he had reſerued for him. In like ſort, a man ſhould chiefly regard theſe ten kindes of benefites that enſue: that is, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of creation, of conſeruation, of redemption, of baptiſme, of calling, of diuine inſpiration, of preſeruation from euill, of the Sarraments, of peculiar grace and priuate prerogatiues which hée hath receiued of his Sauiour, and laſtly, of the glorie which hée expecteth héereafter to haue. And particularly, let him fixe himſelfe vppon the benefite of vocation, whiche is this, that God hath looked ſo long for his conuerſion, and hath ſuffered and ſupported his ſundrie ſortes of ſinne, with ſuch excée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding patience, breathing vpon him eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoones godly motions and diuine inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in the very midſt of his naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie life, thereby to withdrawe him from
<pb facs="tcp:150700:76"/>his iniquities, and to ſtirre him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
               <p>Weighing then with equall balance, this wonderfull liberalitie and benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our Sauiour on the one ſide, and on the other, our ſtubbornneſſe, ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, rebellion, and abhominations committed againſt ſo mercifull &amp; boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous a benefactor, who will not be aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and appalled thereat? who will not rent his cloathes? whoſe eyes will not yéelde ſtreames of teares? whoſe heart and intrailes will not bee conſumed in ſighes? who wil not call all creatures to reuenge and to wrecke their wrath vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a caitiffe ſo ingratefull and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the fourth conſideration, a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſhould conſider the contempt and iniury he hath done to God by his offences: eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming more, and preferring earthly droſſe before his diuine Maieſtie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:150700:76"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>COnſider farther, the deſpight and great wrong y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is done vnto God through ſinne, for that ſo oft as we offend, the iudgement and practiſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of doth ſtill paſſe into our hearts, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth the vnderſtanding, whereby we baniſh all feare of tranſgreſſion, nor we féele not the weight of ſinne, whiche if it were ſet diametrically in the one part before the intereſt of ſin, which is ſome delight, or gaine, or ſteppe of dignitie, or ſuch like, and on the other part the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God, whereby we léeſe vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly God himſelfe, who is the toppe of our felicitie. In ſuch ſort, as though God were conteined in one ballance, and the taſte aforeſaide in the other, and a man placed in the middeſt, deliberating and giuing ſentence which ſhould be reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, deſpiſeth God, to enioy that fléeting delight: what greater contempt, what more ignominie, what ſo great reproach
<pb facs="tcp:150700:77"/>can there bee offered to the diuine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of God, then to preferre and eſtéem better of droſſe and filth, then of Gods excellencie. Wherein we much reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Hebrewes, when Chriſte and <hi>Barabbas</hi> béeing preſented before them, to knowe which ſhould bee deliuered, with one accord they rather choſe <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabbas</hi> then Chriſte. And this is as though we woulde ſay vnto God, we will no more account thée for GOD, but we will adore and haue for our God and finall ende, our owne delightes and proper gaine. For hée that ſo muche regardeth a delight, that he preferreth it before the loue of God, and eſtéemeth and accounteth it of greater price then God himſelfe, aſſayeth to robbe God of his royall dignitie, who is the prop and piller of our beatitude, beſtowing it vpon ſome brickle or beaſtly pleaſure, whiche is as though he would bereaue God of his crowne, and giue it to a creature. What thing can be more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible then this: God commaunded the Heauens béeing ſenceleſſe Creatures,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150700:77"/>that they ſhould féele this defect, and ſhould woonder thereat, ſaying by the Prophet <hi>Ieremie,</hi> O ye Heauens bée aſtonied thereat, and lette your gates cracke with maruelling, for my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple haue offended mee gréeuouſly after two ſortes: They haue forſaken mee the fountaine of the water of life, and they aſſay to aſſwage their thirſt in ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king puddles, which can holde no wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. He then that conſidereth how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſand times hee hath done vnto God the very ſame contempt and iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, what ſhould he not tremble to haue committed ſo gréeuous crimes? ſhould hee not wiſh that his eyes were turned into fountaines of teares, to bewails night and day ſo great euils and exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fifthly, we ought to conſider how much God hateth ſinne, and for the ſame, how many men be ſcourged with ſundry cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb facs="tcp:150700:78"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <p>COnſider the execrable hatred that God beareth to ſinne, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be comprehended in the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of man, for that the malice of ſin is conformable to the maieſtie of the perſon offended. Wherfore as the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and omnipotencie of God is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit, ſo alſo is the malice of ſin committed againſt him. And farther, as the bountie of god is infinit, ſo he hath an infinit ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to wickedneſſe. And yet if thou will know this geare more clearely, and wilt imprint déeper in thy minde the hugeneſſe of this hatred, and therewith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all wilt fixe in thy heart the feare of God (which is the foundation of all our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile) marke the dreadfull and bitter puniſhments y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath executed againſt ſinne, and thereby ſhalt vnderſtand it the better. Theſe puniſhments are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, but thou mayeſt ſet to the view of thy conſideration, the moſt notable amongſt them. As was the wrath of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150700:78"/>God extended vpon his chéefeſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, and all his adherents: Vpon the firſt man, with all his poſteritie: Vpon the whole world, by the generall floud: Vppon the fiue great Cities conſumed with fire and Brimſtone, diſcending from Heauen: Vpon the two ſonnes of <hi>Aron, Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abiu,</hi> becauſe they would offer vp ſacrifice to God with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens fire: Vppon <hi>Dauid,</hi> for his adulterie: Vpon <hi>Saule</hi> for his diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience: Vpon <hi>Hely,</hi> for not chaſtening his Children: Vpon <hi>Anania</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira,</hi> for their auarice: Vppon <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonezer,</hi> for his pride: Vpon <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Niniuie,</hi> and other Citties, which for their diuers offences, were vttterly deſtroyed and left deſolate. Conſider alſo, the fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of hell fire, and the torments thereof, which GOD prouided for the reuenge of ſinne: the ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and puniſhment that his ſonne was forced to endure, before he coulde cure the guilt and griefe of ſinne, which is more terrible then all
<pb facs="tcp:150700:79"/>the reſt, for the worthineſſe of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, vpon whom it was executed. Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe puniſhments, if it bee ſcanned aduiſedly, with his due circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, ſhall much auaile to aduiſe vs of the dreadfull ſeueritie of Gods iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and the mortall hatred he heareth to ſinne, whereby may be driuen into our hearts, the dread of God, and dolour of ſinne.</p>
               <p>He therefore that conſidereth how oft he hath incurred this ſo haynous indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of God, ſhall it not be requiſite that hee ſhrinke and ſhiuer thereat, and that hee with for a ſea of ſorrowfull ſobbes and teares, to quench therewith the furie and flame of Gods hideous hatred enkindled againſt him? A man therefore meditating in his minde with a vehement paſſion of dole, that the mightie Lorde of hoſtes will lay vppon him, all the plagues before mentioned, or at the leaſt ſome part of them: lette him méekely proſtrate himſelfe before the preſence of God, and béeing true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly humbled in the very bottome of his
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150700:79"/>heart, ſay he thus.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>A Prayer.</head>
                           <p>O Supreme Creator of all things, I reckoning in the ſecret records of my minde, my gréeuous guilt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt thy diuine Maieſtie, doo meruaile at my folly, yea at my mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, weighing how benigne and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a patron I haue abandoned. I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe and curſe my ingratitude, ſéeing that from ſuch libertie, I am come to ſo wretched thraldome: I know not what to expect or hope for, but hell, death, and deſperation. For the iuſtice which I cannot ſhunne, doth gall and cruſh my conſcience: yet remember con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe thy infinit mercie and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, which by the teſtimonie of thy Prophet, excelleth all other workes, and by the which in a cortaine manner thou maſtereſt thy ſelfe, ſuddenly a ioyfull ſparke of hope doth recreate my ſore afflicted ſoule. For why ſhould I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre to obtaine pardon of him, who by his Prophets doth ſo oft inuite ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb facs="tcp:150700:80"/>to repentance, ſaying, I wiſh not the death of a ſinner, but rather his conuerſion and life. And thy one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten ſonne by many Parables hath manifeſted vnto vs, howe readie thy remiſſion is to all true penitents.</p>
                           <p>This he ſhewed by the Iewell which was loſt and founde againe: by the prodigall ſonne, whoſe perfect image I acknowledge to be in my ſelfe. For he I am which haue wrongfully renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thée my moſt affectioned father, and hee that waſted his bloud riotouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: and following the purſuites of my fleſhly deſires, haue fled from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleaſant path of thy commaundements, and haue fallen into the beaſtly bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of ſinne, and conſequently, haue béene oppreſſed with extreame diſtreſſe and miſerie. From whence I know not who can reſtore mee home againe, but hee onely from whome I haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolted. Swéete Sauiour, let thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy receiue the man that humply pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth pardon, whom thou haſt graciouſly expected euen till this houre. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150700:80"/>this is not due to my merittes, in ſtead of them, I offer vnto thée all the trauailes and deſerts of thy dearely beloued ſonne, and all the ſorrowe and torments that he hath ſuffered for me.</p>
                           <p>Therefore, moſt mercifull father, for the feruent loue and petitions of thy deare ſonne, forgiue the faults of thy hiſtoyall vaſſall, regarde the noble ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice offered by thy ſonne, and race out of thy remembraunce, the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of thy leaud ſeruaunt. For the raunſome that he hath payde for my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie, ſurpaſſeth farre any my debts or treſpaſſes whatſoeuer. Oh that it would pleaſe thée to put in a payre of balance my leaudneſſe &amp; thy liberalitie, my wickedneſſe and thy woundes, no doubt the peiſe of them would bee more weightie a great deale. For what guilt can bee ſo gréeuous, for which ſuch ſorrowe cannot ſatiſfie ſufficiently? which cannot bee waſhed away with ſuch affliction, with ſo many teares, and with ſuch obedience and humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, with ſuch inuincible patience,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:81"/>and aboue all, with ſuch immeaſurable loue? What crime can be ſo enormous, which may not bee cleanſed with that bloudie ſweat, yea whole flouds of blood? What ſinne is there ſo execrable, which is not cured by Chriſtes death? Oh hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father, I offer here vnto thée, the ſelfe-ſame my Sauiour and Redéemer, Ieſus Chriſt thy ſonne, beloued moſt tenderly. His ſharpe ſorrowes, his ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies incomprchenſible, the which thou knoweſt exactly to be ſuffered for my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: and in ſtead of the contrition which I ought to haue for them, I offer vnto thee his bloudie ſweat: in ſtead of my teares, which I cannot ſhed becauſe of the adamanticall harneſſe of my hart, I offer vnto thée, his humble and ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t praiers, for all my ſlouths and negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. For ende: I offer vnto thée all his loathſome labours, and vertuous exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, his auſtere life, and all that he hath wrought therein, and the bitter torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that he did abide, as a worthie ſacrifice of thy diuine glorie, for all the iniquities wherewith my whole life I haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150700:81"/>thée, and for the good things which I haue omitted and left vndone. Which liueſt and raigneſt for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the ſixt conſideration, a man ſhould thinke vpon death, the laſt iudgement, and bell paines. And how greeuous will be the ſeparation of the ſoule from the bodie, by meanes of death, which by reaſon of diuers accidents occurring then togither, is the very receit of exceſſiue ſorrows &amp; anxie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. VIII.</head>
               <p>TO theſe conſiderations, I wil adde other thrée, out of <hi>Saraſinus</hi> of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> that is, death, iudgement, and ſhe paines of hel, which are a very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry appendix to all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue treated of before. The ſame Doctor telleth vs, that to him that is newly conuerted, nothing
<pb facs="tcp:150700:82"/>is more behouefull and requiſite, then the meditation of death, both for that it repelleth vaine delightes, as alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the practiſe thereof is of ſuch fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie, as the whiche we daily viewe with our eyes, and féele with our hands: yea, we may rather ſay, that our ſureſt portion is with death, and that we dye continually, hauing a bodie ſo corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, that euery houre altereth &amp; chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his ſhape, and neuer reſteth in one eſtate. Like vnto a riuer that paſſeth with a furious and headlong courſe, wherof no part can be marked through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for it running ſwiftly, whileſt ye note one waue, ſtraight it is not the ſame that ye looked vppon before, but is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into another. Many deuout conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations may be had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning death, which the matter it ſelfe yéeldeth ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to him that aduiſedly deliberateth herevpon. Of which, minding to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect a fewe, I doo affirme, that if thou intende to reforme thy life, when thou riſeſt in the morning, perſwade thy ſelfe ſo much as thou maieſt, that the ſame
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150700:82"/>will bee the laſt day of thy life, and diſpoſe of thy ſoule and worldly affaires, in ſuche ſort, as though in verie déede thou ſhouldeſt not liue one houre lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and thinke not that thou deceiueſt thy ſelfe in ſo dooing, for if death may attache thée euery day, thou ſhouldeſt likewiſe daily attende his comming. And farther I ſay vnto thée, that no one day of thy life ſhall paſſe without many negligences, vnleſſe thou doeſt enforce thy ſelfe to beléeue that euery of them is the laſte of thy life. Thinke alſo vppon the dreadfull ſtroke of Death, which becauſe it is ſo vncertaine, ought to bee feared continually: And conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to howe many perilles of death we are ſubiected, and thou ſhalt finde that they are innumerable, as well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bodie as without, in ſo muche that if thou looke warily about thée, thou ſhalt perceiue Death to be payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in euery place, and buſineſſe. Thinke alſo what preſſures and ago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies ſhall aſſault thée at the poynte of death.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:150700:83"/>
               <p>To this conſideration, it ſhall aſſiſt thée much, to beholde ſometimes a man dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Marke the accidents and paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full paſſions of that houre, howe his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die lyeth forſaken of naturall heats, his ſences without force or moouing, as though it were a very ſtone, the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities and vttermoſt parts waxe colds, the face is turned into the colour of leade, the bowles of the eyes dipped in, the mouth full of fome, the tongue ſwol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, the necke winding to euery ſide. Then marke alſo howe the breſt bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and panteth, and is readie to burſt aſunder with paine, the lippes waxe blewe, the téethe become dumbe. Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all the bodie diſſoluing it ſelfe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forſaken of the ſoule, with ſorrowe ineſtimable the man reſteth a lumpe of earth. Thou perceiuing and viewing well ſuch perplexities in other, maieſt likewiſe repreſent the ſame ſpectacle in thy ſelfe, imagining that the Phiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians haue nowe giuen thée ouer, as knowing the maladie to bee incurable; thy friendes and kinſfolkes about thy
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150700:83"/>bedde, whoſe preſence ſhal augment the griefe of thy departure. O how dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhall that ſeparation be, where welth ſhall not aſſwage thy woe, but ſhall ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther plunge thée déeper in the gulfe of calamities, neyther ſhall honours aſſiſt thée? yea thou ſhalt leaue them with like vehement ſmart, as thou gotteſt them with gréedie deſire, and for thy wonted delights, ſhalt reape the fruites of a gnawing conſcience. What then wilt thou doo béeing brought to this poynt? what counſell wilt thou then take? To go out of thy bodie will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable, to abide there impoſſible, to deferre thy departure, cannot be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thée, neither maieſt thou returne to thy ſenſuall delightes, which nowe are ſenſleſſe togither, but knowing thy ſelfe, and ſcanning them more narrowly, ſhalt bee abaſhed at thine owne brutiſh behauiour, and if it were poſſible, woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt flie from thy ſelfe. Shalt ſée thy ſelfe beſet with horrible monſters, that is, with thine owne ſinnes, of whom whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſoeuer thou wandreſt, thou ſhalt
<pb facs="tcp:150700:84"/>be purſued and hedged in, all that is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſhall ſéeme vnto thée as the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye, and ſhalt know the time to come to be infinite. Then mayeſt thou well ſay with the Prophet, The dolours and daungers of death hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed mée rounde about, and the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of hell hath aſſaulted mée. By this minding and meditation of death, thou ſhalt acquire many great commodities. Firſt, thou ſhalt be ſtirred and incenſed to the ſeruice of God, the feare of whom is the foundation of wiſedome, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of true bliſſe. Endeuour there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſo to arme and addreſſe thy ſelfe at all poynts, that thou be not vanquiſhed by ſinne. Farther, ſhalt viewe thine owne wretchedneſſe and infirmities, whiche will ſerue as a corzie to qual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie the ſwelling rancor of pride, and to eſtabliſh humilitie, the very quéene and guide of all other vertues. And ſhalt eaſily reiect hatefull auarice, and gréedie gaping for earthly vanities. For the memorie of death, cauſeth thée to knowe, that none of theſe thinges
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150700:84"/>can be called thine, which thou canſt not carry with thee out of this world. And thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in this exerciſe, vnwares thy dread ſhall be turned into deſire, and death ſhall not ſéem ſo terrible vnto thée, for that it depriueth thée of thy temporall life, as delightful and acceptable, becauſe it giueth ende to ſo many gréefes and miſeries, and giueth enterance to life and light eternall. And thou ſhalt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue howe little cauſe thou haddeſt to complaine, or to be ſorie, weighing that whileſt thy bodie doth periſhe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume in the graue, thy ſoule liueth bliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in heauen, with a firme beléefe to riſe againe at the laſt day to life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the ſeuenth conſideration, ought to be premeditated how ſeuere and rigorous Chriſt will be at the day of iudgement: for that his countenance will then declare to the wickid beholders, nothing elſe but fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious wrath and reuenge, which none can eſcape, for there must be giuen vp an exact account of all thinges done and
<pb facs="tcp:150700:85"/>thought of in this world.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>EAch man proueth and perceiueth in himſelfe by often experience, that his vnderſtanding, by the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of ſome fearfull obiect or weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie conſideration, retireth and coucheth cloſely within it ſelfe, and for that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, repelleth eaſily all other idle ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations. For which cauſe, it is moſt proſitable counſayle, that a ſinner at his firſt conuerſion exerciſe himſelfe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly in ſuch cogitations, for that by this meanes, péeuiſh fanſies, ſometime through dread, ſometime through won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, will be either brideled or baniſhed quite. If the memorie of death, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaide, hath ſuch force to cut off, and to reſtraine our vaine and bagraum thoughts: howe much more may this be done by the remembraunce of that which inſueth after death immediately, whiche is Gods iudgement, and the paines of hell? By which meditations,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:85"/>if thou often thinke vpon them, ſhall be brought to paſſe, that which <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtick</hi> affirmeth, Remember thy daies, (whereby hee meaneth that which then ſhall happen vnto thee) and thou ſhalt neuer doo amiſſe. S. <hi>Hierome</hi> not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iuſt cauſe ſaid: Whether I eate or drinke, mee thinkes ſtill I heare the ſounde of the Trumpet buzzing in my eares: Ariſe from death, and come to your iudgement. Which howe terrible it ſhall be cannot be imagined, ſith all other terrours or tragedies whatſoeuer in compariſon of this is nothing at all. Many times God hath manifeſted his iudgements in this worlde, as when hee drowned the worlde with the great floud: when hee burned <hi>Sodome</hi> and the Cities adioyning: when he ſtrooke <hi>Egypt</hi> with diuers dreadfull plagues: when he made the earth to open in the deſert to ſwallow vp ſinners: all which iudgements, beeing compared to that generall iudgement which ſhall be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in the laſt day, are but ſhadowes, but ſhewes, and figures of the veritie.
<pb facs="tcp:150700:86"/>If then thou deſire to come to thy ſelfe, and to gather thy wits togither with the remembraunce of this, repreſent to thy imagination the terribleneſſe of Chriſt thy iudge, whoſe countenance ſhall declare nothing elſe but rigour and reuenge, as at the firſt comming he ſhewed mildeneſſe altogither. From whom thou canſt not appeale to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe he is ſupreme Iudge: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther canſt thou auoide his furie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is moſt puiſſant: and for that hee is the very fountaine and God of knowledge, nothing can be concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from him. And becauſe he hateth iniquitie out of meaſure, hee will not ſuffer any ſinne to be vnreuenged.</p>
               <p>There thou muſt bee accountable of all thy tranſgreſſions, debts, and treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, whereof if the leaſt be inough to put thée in extreame danger and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie, who can make ſatiſfaction for ſo many debtes and arrerages, as ſhall bee exacted at thy handes? Then thou ſhalt bee examined how thou haſt veſtowed thy time, howe thou haſte
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150700:86"/>ordered thy body, howe thou haſt go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerned thy ſences, and how thou haſt guided thy heart, howe thou haſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered to the diuine inſpirations, how thou haſte acknowledged ſo many cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſies. In the which accuſation, thou ſhalt bee conuinced with ſo many wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, as are the creatures which thou haſt abuſed by ſinne, which then will be ſo ſtirred to reuenge the wrong done vnto their creator, that if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, thoſe which are immortall would dye with feare. For it ſhall be a horror ineſtimable, to ſée the worlde all on fire: the buildings and princely Pallaces ouerthrowne and torne in péeces: the earth to tremble: to viewe the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to chaunge theyr courſe: the Sunne to bee darkened: the Moone and Starres to léeſe theyr light: to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the death and deſtruction of all creatures: the open gaping of graues: to heare the voyce of the terrible trumpe, and wofull waylings of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: to marke the diſcouering of conſciences: to regarde the mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous
<pb facs="tcp:150700:87"/>deformed diuels, and ſhe in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall furnace ſparkling with furious flakes. But of all other things ſhall be moſt terrible to looke vppon, the victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous flagge of the Croſſe, clittering in the ayre, with all the enſignes of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious paſſion of our Sauiour: To ſée the Iudge to charge his enemies for the making fruſtrate, yea the reitteration of ſo many torments as hee hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for their redemption. Who might more eaſily endure the ſmart of hell paines, then to ſée themſelues ſo accuſed and accurſed of the Lord of bountie and courteſie, and to be expelled from his preſence to perpetuall puniſhment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the eight conſideration, we ought to premeditate vpon the intollerable terrour of hell paines, which ſhall be perpetuall. But of al thoſe torments, the moſt greeuous is the loſſe and lacke of Gods chearefull countenance, without any hope for euer to gaine it againe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:150700:87"/>
               <head>CHAP. X.</head>
               <p>BUt it may ſo chance, that mauger thy might, for all theſe conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ydle thoughts will not forſake thee, though it muſt néedes bee a ſounde fléepe and a very drowzie dreame, that will not bee awaked with ſuch incita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Yet thou muſt not be diſcomfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but howe much more difficults doo ariſe, ſo much the more ſtoutly thou ſhouldeſt ſtriue to atchieue thy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe. Aſſay then whither the ſearch of hell paines will bee more behouefull vnto thée, concerning which, two things are chiefly to be noted, that is, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemencie of their ſmart, and the time of their continuance. The leaſt of theſe is able to mollifie the moſt ſtubborne and ſtony heart of the worlde: but the which is not mooued neither with the one nor with the other, is eyther dead in his ſoule, or elſe beléeueth not that which the Chriſtian faith ſheweth.</p>
               <p>For though the greatneſſe of hell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cannot bee imagined nor expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
<pb facs="tcp:150700:88"/>filled with moſt iuſt feare. If thou ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome thy ſelfe to ſuch exerciſes, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> doeſt perſeuer therin, in ſhort ſpace thou thalt become a newe man, for by theſe meditations thy minde ſhall be brought to deſpiſe the world, to ſhun ſinne, to fear theſe paines, and to loue vertue. And though at the beginning thou bee appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and affrighted vehemently, yet hand patience a while, for thy colde feare ſhall be qualified and tempered with the heat of loue, as the black night is turned by little and little into the bright ſhining day.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>EINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
